<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Ashton Kemerling]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-29T21:34:31-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ashton Kemerling]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ashtonkemerling@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Java Without If]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2017/01/26/java-without-if/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-26T19:54:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2017/01/26/java-without-if</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past year my team has been doing something shocking to a lot of
engineers: we&#8217;re favoring pure Java over Clojure. We aren&#8217;t rewriting all our
Clojure code, but we definitely prefer Java for green field projects.</p>

<p>This post is not going to be a compare and contrast between the two, nor am I
going to bash Clojure. Language compare and contrast posts always descend into
flame wars, and it&#8217;s very easy to confuse the result of hard lessons learned
with the benefits of a new language.</p>

<p>Instead I&#8217;d like to highlight a very strange aspect of our new Java development,
and I hope that you&#8217;re sitting down for this. Except tests, I have fewer than a
dozen <code>if</code> statements currently committed in our Java codebase.</p>

<p>It would be easy to assume that we&#8217;re just using Java&#8217;s method dispatch to
replace if statements; rather than inspecting data and calling if/else on it,
you can use interfaces and count on the implementation to provide the difference
in behavior. But such an explanation is insufficient: objects don&#8217;t magically
construct themselves from unstructured data, and Clojure is not without its own
dynamic dispatch <a href="https://clojure.org/reference/multimethods">facilities</a>.</p>

<p>Ultimately the real explanation for this strange code design lies in my
colleague&#8217;s extremely exceptional <a href="https://github.com/palatable/lambda">Lambda</a>
library. It contains a lot of things that a Haskell/Scala developer would
recognize such as Either types, function utilities, coproducts, etc. etc.</p>

<p>In particular I&#8217;d like to draw your eye to the Either type, which has replaced
the vast majority of our explicit <code>if</code> calls. Either is the logical
successor to the Java
8 <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/Optional.html">Optional</a>
type. Optional represents the presence of a value of type <code>T</code> with
 <code>Optional::of</code>, or it&#8217;s absence with <code>Optional::empty</code>. Either on the
other hand is parameterized to two values, L and R, and represents the presence
of either a value of type L, <em>or</em> a value of type R.</p>

<p>Why is this a logical extension of <code>Optional</code>? Because while Optional is
used to represent a result that may have no value (replacing a null), Either is
used to represent a result that might have been a failure, replacing a thrown
exception, with convention being that left side values represent failure and
right side values representing success.</p>

<p>So, what does that buy us? Well, consider what Optional gets us in the following code snippets.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='java'><span class='line'><span class="n">String</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Helper</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">functionOne</span><span class="o">();</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="kc">null</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Helper</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">functionTwo</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="o">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Helper</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">functionThree</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="o">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="kc">null</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">...</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='java'><span class='line'><span class="n">Optional</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">String</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Helper</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">functionOne</span><span class="o">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>                           <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">map</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nl">Helper:</span><span class="o">:</span><span class="n">functionTwo</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>                           <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">flatMap</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nl">Helper:</span><span class="o">:</span><span class="n">functionThree</span><span class="o">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Optional gives us the ability to say &#8220;if a value exists, apply this function to
it&#8221; repeatedly. It also gives us the ability to chain successive calls that
return Optionals together with the <code>flatMap</code> function, eliminating the need
for unsightly and error prone manual null checks. It&#8217;s also safe for <code>map</code>
and <code>flatMap</code> to go from <code>Optional&lt;A&gt;</code> to <code>Optional&lt;B&gt;</code>, which might
eliminate the need for intermediate variables in your code.</p>

<p>Either give us much of the same, but with the ability to represent <strong>why</strong> the
computation failed with left values, along with the ability to chain together
functions working on an Either type. All of the greatest hits of functional
programming are provided for Either, including <code>map</code>, <code>flatMap</code>, and <code>filter</code>.</p>

<p>As a concrete example, imagine a hypothetical JSON parsing library. Parsing is
tricky business, you&#8217;re all but guaranteed that a failure will happen at
runtime. So how do you handle it? Previously you had 4 choices.</p>

<ul>
<li>return null</li>
<li>return Optional&lt;ParsedType></li>
<li>checked exception</li>
<li>unchecked exception</li>
</ul>


<p>Null is obviously bad, and unchecked exceptions are also risky. Checked
exceptions guarantee that someone will deal with the issue, but they are
extremely annoying, and might result in disparate and different exception
handlers all over the place. Optional is nice, it&#8217;s safer than null and marks in
the type signature that failure is an option, but it&#8217;s a bit lacking on
explaining <strong>why</strong> a failure occurred.</p>

<p>What if instead this library returned <code>Either&lt;Exception, JsonNode&gt;</code>, or even
 <code>Either&lt;Set&lt;String&gt;, JsonNode&gt;</code>? The potential for failure is in the type
signature again, we don&#8217;t need a try/catch, but if we want the unwrapped
JsonNode we have to deal with the potential for a left value. And any functions
we have that operate only on JsonNode can be passed in using the <code>map</code>
function, making chaining a breeze.</p>

<p>Better still we can write other functions that might fail in this form, such as
JSON validation, so that we can chain them together using <code>flatMap</code>. If the
json parsing has failed, flatMap does nothing (it only works on right values),
replacing the need for successive null checks, nested try/catch blocks, or
complicated state checking during exception handling to return the correct
value.</p>

<p>As a result of all this, you can easily imagine a JSON API endpoint looking
something like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='java'><span class='line'><span class="kd">public</span> <span class="n">HttpResponse</span> <span class="nf">handle</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">HttpRequest</span> <span class="n">request</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">JsonParser</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">parse</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">request</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">getBody</span><span class="o">())</span>
</span><span class='line'>                     <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">flatMap</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nl">Validator:</span><span class="o">:</span><span class="n">validate</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>                     <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">map</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nl">ServiceObject:</span><span class="o">:</span><span class="n">businessLogic</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>                     <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">flatMap</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nl">JsonGenerator:</span><span class="o">:</span><span class="n">generate</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>                     <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">match</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">l</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="n">HttpResponse</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">internalServerError</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">l</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">getMessage</span><span class="o">()),</span>
</span><span class='line'>                            <span class="n">r</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="n">HttpResponse</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">ok</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">l</span><span class="o">));</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>All the potential failure cases are covered by returning an Either rather than
throwing an exception. The very last step is <code>match</code>, which takes two
functions to unify a potential left or right value to the exact same type, which
in this case is <code>HttpResponse</code>.</p>

<h3>What does this get me?</h3>

<p>Well, first off I think it&#8217;s beautiful. I know that&#8217;s a subjective call, but the
data flowing neatly from top to bottom without huge nesting if cases and early
return values is very aesthetically pleasing to me.</p>

<p>More functionally it&#8217;s easier to refactor with the help of the compiler. If I
want to add different return status codes to match different scenarios, the
compiler helps me out a lot more than if I&#8217;m adding an extra return case. If I
convert the left side to a HttpResponse early, the compiler will helpfully
remind me that the later flatMap calls cannot change <code>Either&lt;HttpResponse,
JsonNode&gt;</code> to <code>Either&lt;Exception, BusinessObject&gt;</code>. Such changes are easily
fixed once the compiler has pointed it out, but extremely hard to find on your
own.</p>

<p>But most fundamentally is that we&#8217;ve encoded our code&#8217;s states in the type
system, not variable states. The potential for JSON parsing to fail is encoded
in its type, not in the potential for a variable to null, or false, or for an
exception to have been thrown. You&#8217;re leaning on the compiler to tell you if
you&#8217;ve handled the failure cases properly, as the code won&#8217;t compile otherwise.
Now instead of testing for runtime exceptions you only test to make sure that
your business logic is correct.</p>

<p>If you&#8217;ve ever been interested in what the Haskell or Scala developers have been
talking about with functional type safety, I&#8217;d highly recommend taking a look at
Lambda to get a taste of it in Java.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Increasing Frustration With Clojure]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2016/06/11/my-increasing-frustration-with-clojure/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-11T06:24:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2016/06/11/my-increasing-frustration-with-clojure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Edit: TL;DR: This is about how bugs in Clojure are handled by the Clojure Team, not just complaints about specific bugs I&#8217;ve seen.</strong></p>

<p>First off, this is not a &#8220;I&#8217;m quiting in disgust&#8221; post. Those are childish and a waste of everyone&#8217;s time. But this is a post of frustration as I watch something I really like being slowly allowed to get worse.</p>

<p>First off, some history. My first job out of College was in Common Lisp, and I love/hated it. The power it brought and the pain it brought were both one and the same. No modern libraries, no modern build tools (this was before <a href="https://www.quicklisp.org/beta/">QuickLisp</a>). One on hand, I <em>loved</em> working with paredit and Emacs, being able to quickly fly about my code and manipulate it in blocks rather than line by line. On the other, I couldn&#8217;t help but be envious of those who could actually ask for help from a functioning open source community.</p>

<p>A few years of Python, Ruby, and Javascript later, I found Clojure. And I thought I&#8217;d found the solution to literally all of the things. Paredit works again? Check. A thriving open source community? You got it. Deploy as a Jar rather than CL&#8217;s hilarious &#8220;dump the state of a running program and call it good&#8221; setup? Fuck. Yes.</p>

<p>And beyond the superficial things, there was a lot to love, especially coming from a more recent brush with Ruby on Rails. Clojure makes it very easy to make things <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Referential_transparency">referentially transparent</a>, and it tends to favor explicit calling semantics over convention (or more derisively, &#8220;magic&#8221;). This means that a Clojure code base will require more plumbing code, but that also means it&#8217;s possible to navigate to the code that does routing and understand how it works, no more having to search through your framework&#8217;s codebase just because they do dynamic method creation and method_missing magic.</p>

<p> As far as I was concerned, the editor was the only weak point for Clojure. Back when I got into Clojure Cursive was still brand new, Emacs really was the only editor that was worth using and even it had some stability and usability issues. But I assumed that continued interest would stabilize Emacs, bring Vim up to speed, and improve Cursive to the point where it would be competitive with Emacs/Vim.</p>

<p> But all was not well, and if I&#8217;d paid attention I might have noticed a few places where the core Clojure&#8217;s teams priorities didn&#8217;t seem to make much sense to me. And now that I work in Clojure professionally, I really cannot ignore them or remain silent about them any more.</p>

<p> The core Clojure team prefers green field development over improvements and bug fixes to existing code to a degree that deeply worries me. I no longer trust that any issues I find stand a chance of getting fixed, as all the bugs we&#8217;ve posted are either in limbo, or flat out rejected. Multiple members of my team have given up on posting new bugs because they have no faith that it&#8217;ll help anyone.</p>

<p> These are pretty heavy and vague accusations, so I&#8217;m gonna break this down a bit to make it clearer and easier to digest.</p>

<h2>Ignorance or Apathy of Underlying Principles</h2>

<p> Programming isn&#8217;t math per-se, especially in a language that&#8217;s not explicitly based on Category or Type theory. That said a lot of the things that we do are backed or defined by mathematics, and to ignore that is to guarantee bugs. This is most clear in clojure.set which contains functions that are supposed to mirror the definitions created by Set Theory like <code>union</code>, <code>difference</code>, <code>intersection</code>, etc.</p>

<p> And the namespace is completely riddled with bugs. <code>union</code> returns duplicates if some of the inputs are lists instead of sets <em>depending on their length</em>. <code>intersection</code> will either return nonsense values or throw a ClassCastException if you provide it anything other than sets, again dependent on data.</p>

<p>On their own, this is no big deal. Bugs happen, there&#8217;s really no point in berating people just because they made a mistake. Instead the bug gets fixed as best and as soon as reality allows and we all move on. In fact, for the above bugs there are two possible fixes: raise an IllegalArgumentException if anything other than sets are provided, or coerce lists and vectors to sets before continuing. Both of these approaches are valid due to the fact that this is a dynamic language that defaults to immutable collection semantics; which one you pick is then a matter of how you want to affect your downstream users.</p>

<p>Oh wait, some of these bugs were filed in <em>2009</em>, 7 fucking years ago! Here comes the berating. These functions are <strong>tiny</strong>, a simple implementation of <code>union</code> is one line. And while they&#8217;re heavily used, they&#8217;re simple in usage and signature; no need to change a lot of call sites to fix this bug. There are only two reasons to explain why these bugs have not been fix; they either do not understand that this is an issue, or they do not care.</p>

<p>Actually, their comments on the issues lets us know that they do not understand that this is an issue. Rich Hickey said in 2009 &#8220;the fact that these functions happen to work when the second argument is not a set is an implementation artifact and not a promise of the interface&#8221;. How you define getting the wrong type with nonsense values counts as &#8220;working&#8221; is beyond me. Is it just because it doesn&#8217;t throw an Exception? Anyone here prefer bad data instead of exceptions when dealing with functions like this? I doubt it.</p>

<h2>Inconsistency Between Best Practices and Clojure Implementation</h2>

<p>Clojure includes a pretty powerful concept called protocols. Basically a protocol is an interface that can be added to classes after the fact, and lets you dispatch to different behavior silently at run time.</p>

<p>This is pretty neat, it lets you abstract over multiple data types and include Java classes in the fun. For example ISeq provides all the methods needed to iterate over a collection and it works with all the Clojure and Java data types. So you can use Clojure&#8217;s <code>map</code> function over its own data types and Java&#8217;s because it depends on the seq interface.</p>

<p>As you can imagine, this is the recommended way to work with things. Rather than having to do <code>cond</code> or <code>if</code> logic on various classes, define and use an appropriate protocol and you&#8217;re good to go!</p>

<p>It sounds like a good theory doesn&#8217;t it? But Clojure itself doesn&#8217;t actually do this. Clojure.core contains 89 calls to <code>instance?</code> in order to check runtime type, instead of the helper methods to check for protocol implementation.</p>

<p><a href="http://dev.clojure.org/jira/browse/CLJ-1944">Here</a> is a bug found by my colleague that highlights this issue. List and Vector are both seqs, but <code>into</code> for a map only accepts vectors, lists causes a ClassCastException. This is kind of nuts because an IllegalArgumentException makes more sense, and there&#8217;s no practical reason to differentiate between a list of two elements and a vector of two elements. Actually, Clojure considers <code>[1 2]</code> and <code>(list 1 2)</code> to be equal, so this really makes no sense</p>

<p>Even more obnoxious, it was closed as wontfix. Apparently a single sentence in the docs is good enough for the Clojure team, as well as a paper-thin argument about performance on a 2 element list. So not only is this just broken in a barely documented and very surprising way, Clojure itself ends up programmed in a way that isn&#8217;t recommended by the Clojure docs.</p>

<p>This has spread to other projects. <a href="https://github.com/omcljs/om">Om</a> has a bug where lists aren&#8217;t acceptable in its data structures, only maps sets and vectors. To say that I was treated pretty <a href="https://github.com/omcljs/om/issues/246">shabbily</a> by David Nolen on this issue almost goes without saying. Naturally the intro <a href="https://github.com/omcljs/om/wiki/Basic-Tutorial">docs</a> barely call this out, and the docs <a href="https://github.com/omcljs/om/wiki/Cursors">dedicated</a> to the troubled component does not mention this at all. To be fair, the <a href="https://github.com/omcljs/om/wiki/Troubleshooting">troubleshooting guide</a> explains this, but in my opinion that&#8217;s probably a clue that the bug is common enough that you should find a fix for it.</p>

<h2>Show Stopping Bugs Remain Untouched</h2>

<p>There are a shocking number of big, bad bugs hiding in the Clojure Jira, some really old</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://dev.clojure.org/jira/browse/CLJ-308">This one</a> about fixing with-open for Clojure defined stuff provided a patch 5 years ago.</li>
<li><a href="http://dev.clojure.org/jira/browse/CLJ-440">Calling VarArgs Successfully</a> from 6 years ago.</li>
<li><a href="http://dev.clojure.org/jira/browse/CLJ-700">Contains? broken for transient collections</a> from 5 years ago. But it&#8217;s due for this version, so cross your fingers!</li>
<li><a href="http://dev.clojure.org/jira/browse/CLJ-1463">Bizarrely Defensive Response</a> for a minor code review.</li>
<li><a href="http://dev.clojure.org/jira/browse/CLJ-1741">Duelling ClassLoaders</a> first discovered last year. This one breaks our editors constantly. Not even assigned.</li>
</ul>


<p>I could go on, but I feel that I&#8217;ve made my point. Bugs, even major ones are either closed as &#8220;wontfix&#8221;, or are ignored for years despite the pain felt by users. That&#8217;s not even covering the dismissive and distrustful attitude given in some of the replies.</p>

<h2>Strange Priorities</h2>

<p>The Clojure team appears to be super focused on new features, at the exclusion of existing namespaces. The big highlights from the past year or so have been Transit, Transducers, and Spec.</p>

<p>These are okay, I guess. We use transit a bit, and it&#8217;s kinda cool. But we really don&#8217;t use 90% of its features, it&#8217;s basically JSON for us that can convert numbers to BigDecimals.</p>

<p>We have yet to find a place that Transducers would help us. They&#8217;re neat enough, but the built in lazy sequences are working A-OK for us, so we don&#8217;t really feel the need to change over.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m not holding my breath for Spec. It doesn&#8217;t fix anything for me that other libraries aren&#8217;t already providing.</p>

<p>Know what hasn&#8217;t seen any major improvements in forever? Clojure.test. Clojure.Test is frankly sad. Fixtures are done via some global state, and you can&#8217;t even setup fixtures to work across the entire test suite. Need a database to run functional tests? Well either you need to override the main test runner (good luck running individual tests now!) or you have to setup each namespace to open and close its own database connection (don&#8217;t forget, or your DBA will wonder why Emacs has 1000+ database connections). I&#8217;m 100% behind the idea that I&#8217;ll have to write a bit of glue code, but without anywhere to <em>put</em> that code I&#8217;m kind of screwed.</p>

<p>And then there is the <code>is</code> function. It&#8217;s literally the only assertion provided by clojure.test. It&#8217;s this fancy little macro that grabs its body, evaluates it, then uses the body to produce a human readable message about the failure.</p>

<p>And it&#8217;s garbage. The fact that <a href="https://github.com/pjstadig/humane-test-output">plugins</a> exist to make this easier on the eyes should tell you everything you need to know. Oh but don&#8217;t use that with Emacs/Cider! It&#8217;ll crash the Cider plugin, which is trying to parse the default output.</p>

<p>Back when I used Emacs, I had a stash on my box that disabled AOT, pedantic checking, and the humane-test-output plugin from my project.clj in order to use Cider. Without that stash applied Cider wouldn&#8217;t start, couldn&#8217;t reload code, and would crash when running tests. Now that I use Cursive that&#8217;s less of an issue, but it&#8217;s still kind of nuts I had to decide between a working editor and readable output when I ran <code>lein test</code></p>

<p>Sorry, I didn&#8217;t even highlight the craziest bit of that last paragraph, did you catch it? I had to disable humane-test-output from my <em>project.clj</em>. That&#8217;s because you install it by injecting some code in project.clj that <strong>redefines</strong> some multi-methods, because there&#8217;s no plugin architecture. How nuts is that?</p>

<p>Now I might hear you say &#8220;You don&#8217;t have to use clojure.test!&#8221;, and you&#8217;re right. But clojure.test has clearly won in the Clojure testing namespace. The only real competitors for clojure.test are <a href="https://github.com/slagyr/speclj">Speclj</a> and <a href="https://github.com/marick/Midje">Midje</a>. I&#8217;ve literally never met someone in person that&#8217;s used Speclj, and Midje is super polarizing because it&#8217;s basically a collection of magic macros. The fact that the second entry for Midje is about CircleCI rewriting from Midje to clojure.test should tell you a lot.</p>

<p>So why don&#8217;t we have more creature comforts for clojure.test? I&#8217;m not really sure. As far as I can tell the change to it was the inclusion of <a href="https://github.com/clojure/test.check">test.check</a>, but that really was nothing more than simple-check getting renamed and transferred to Clojure ownership.</p>

<h1>Okay, Now What?</h1>

<p>As I stated before, this isn&#8217;t a &#8220;I&#8217;m quitting Clojure!&#8221; post. Partly this is because I work in Clojure on a daily basis, and I both like my job and am professional enough to keep working despite my complaints. And partly this is because I do not have a replacement for Clojure in mind for my own personal projects. But off the top of my head, there are the things I&#8217;d like to see fixed in the Clojure areas.</p>

<ul>
<li>More love for clojure.test.</li>
<li>No tolerance for bugs that result in bad-data. Built in functions should either work, or throw an understandable exception.</li>
<li>Friendlier responses in Jira. Someone who has gone to the work to sign up and try to help out should be treated with more respect.</li>
<li>Fix underlying compiler bugs before adding features. The other way only codifies bad behavior and guarantees that it cannot be fixed.</li>
<li>Understand that if enough people have the same issue, it&#8217;s the codes fault and a FAQ entry is <strong>not</strong> good enough.</li>
</ul>


<p>Basically I want Clojure to be a simple to use language backed by a friendly and active community. What I see now is drifting in the wrong direction, and I&#8217;d like to see that corrected.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Integrating Test.Check and Javascript]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/09/25/integrating-test-dot-check-and-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-25T08:41:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/09/25/integrating-test-dot-check-and-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Introduction</h1>

<p>I was recently on
<a href="http://blog.cognitect.com/cognicast/ashton-kemerling-064">The Cognicast</a>
with Craig Andera where we discussed using Generative Testing on a large
non-Clojure(script) codebase, in particular Ruby on Rails and
Backbonejs. If you haven&#8217;t listened to the show yet I highly recommend
it first.</p>

<p>As I promised on the show, I&#8217;d like to share how we used Test.Check to
test our Backbone.js code base. Our overall strategy for testing
Javascript is going to be:</p>

<ol>
<li>Compile JS into one file (just like prod).</li>
<li>Compile tests into a single file.</li>
<li>Combine them in a PhantomJS process.</li>
<li>Let the tests do their thing.</li>
</ol>


<p>While we have been super pleased with the results of Generative Testing,
there have been some hurdles for getting it to work for us. In this post
I&#8217;m going to go over how to setup Test.Check to work with your
Javascript app, and how to dodge all the pitfalls I found.</p>

<p>Here are the challenges that lie between us and Generative Testing bliss.</p>

<ol>
<li>Picking the right library</li>
<li>Setting up Leiningen &amp; Cljsbuild</li>
<li>Dodge PhantomJS issues</li>
<li>Avoid mangling your app, and defeating dueling dependencies</li>
</ol>


<h1>Picking the Right Library</h1>

<p>First of all, there are two libraries that exist,
<a href="https://github.com/clojure/test.check">Test.Check</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/cemerick/double-check">DoubleCheck</a>. Because
Test.Check is an official Clojure library it is Clojure (JVM) only, so I
recommend DoubleCheck (maintained by Chas Emerick) which is capable of
cross compiling to Clojure and Clojurescript.</p>

<p>The only catch with DoubleCheck is that it&#8217;s not currently possible to
segregate tests via metadata for running in groups. But with the way we
will be running these tests that won&#8217;t be an issue.</p>

<h1>Setting up Leiningen</h1>

<p>First step, install <a href="http://leiningen.org/">Leiningen</a> and create a
project.clj wherever you Javascript code is. We&#8217;re going to use
<a href="https://github.com/emezeske/lein-cljsbuild">Cljsbuild</a> to compile our
testing code for execution. I in put my test code in test/cljs (because
I have clj and cljs based tests), and send the compiled output to
tmp/tracker-cljs.js. Note: this guide <em>only works for Clojurescript
0.0-2234</em>, I need to figure out why the latest build of Clojurescript
doesn&#8217;t work.</p>

<p>I highly recommend you send the output of the compilation process to
either a temporary or gitignored location. The output will be fairly
large, and it will bog down your repository with its size.</p>

<p>I don&#8217;t want to duplicate the Cljsbuild how-to, so if you don&#8217;t know how
to make it work, you should check their docs. Our project.clj is
reproduced at the bottom of this post if you have issues.</p>

<p>At this point, we can write the simplest test possible:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='clojure'><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">ns </span><span class="nv">tracker-cljs.simple-test</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">:require</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clojure.test.check</span> <span class="ss">:as</span> <span class="nv">core</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clojure.test.check.generators</span> <span class="ss">:as</span> <span class="nv">gen</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clojure.test.check.properties</span> <span class="ss">:as</span> <span class="nv">prop</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">cemerick.cljs.test</span> <span class="ss">:as</span> <span class="nv">t</span><span class="p">])</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">:require-macros</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clojure.test.check.clojure-test</span> <span class="ss">:refer</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">defspec</span><span class="p">)]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                   <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clojure.test.check.properties</span> <span class="ss">:refer</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">for-all</span><span class="p">)]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                   <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">cemerick.cljs.test</span> <span class="ss">:refer</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">is</span><span class="p">)]))</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">defspec</span> <span class="nv">simple-test</span> <span class="mi">10</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">for-all</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">v</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">gen/such-that</span> <span class="nv">gen/not-empty</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">gen/vector</span> <span class="nv">gen/int</span><span class="p">))]</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">println </span><span class="nv">v</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">true</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p></p>

<h1>PhantomJS issues.</h1>

<p>In order to run the tests, you would typically have a :tests section in
:cljsbuild that looks like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='clojure'><span class='line'><span class="ss">:test-commands</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="s">&quot;unit-tests&quot;</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="s">&quot;phantomjs&quot;</span> <span class="ss">:runner</span>
</span><span class='line'>                                          <span class="s">&quot;compiled-application.js&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>                                          <span class="s">&quot;tmp/compiled-tests.js&quot;</span><span class="p">]}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This will load our JS into the app, along with the tests, and then run
them. But you might notice errors that look like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='clojure'><span class='line'><span class="nv">SECURITY_ERR</span><span class="err">:</span> <span class="nv">DOM</span> <span class="nv">Exception</span> <span class="mi">18</span><span class="err">:</span> <span class="nv">An</span> <span class="nv">attempt</span> <span class="nv">was</span> <span class="nv">made</span> <span class="nv">to</span> <span class="nv">break</span> <span class="nv">through</span> <span class="nv">the</span> <span class="nv">security</span> <span class="nv">policy</span> <span class="nv">of</span> <span class="nv">the</span> <span class="nv">user</span> <span class="nv">agent.</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>That means that your app code is trying to access local storage, and
PhantomJS does not like it when you do that without loading a
webpage. The solution for this is to start a server so we have a page to
visit, and visit it via PhantomJS. So on Tracker we use the following
two bits of code.</p>

<p>generative_runner.js, to visit the actual page:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
<span class='line-number'>33</span>
<span class='line-number'>34</span>
<span class='line-number'>35</span>
<span class='line-number'>36</span>
<span class='line-number'>37</span>
<span class='line-number'>38</span>
<span class='line-number'>39</span>
<span class='line-number'>40</span>
<span class='line-number'>41</span>
<span class='line-number'>42</span>
<span class='line-number'>43</span>
<span class='line-number'>44</span>
<span class='line-number'>45</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='clojure'><span class='line'><span class="nv">//</span> <span class="nv">reusable</span> <span class="nv">PhantomJS</span> <span class="nv">script</span> <span class="nb">for </span><span class="nv">running</span> <span class="nv">clojurescript.test</span> <span class="nv">tests</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">//</span> <span class="nv">see</span> <span class="nv">http</span><span class="ss">://github.com/cemerick/clojurescript.test</span> <span class="nb">for </span><span class="nv">more</span> <span class="nv">info</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">var </span><span class="nv">page</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">&#39;webpage</span><span class="o">&#39;</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="nv">.create</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">page.onResourceError</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">resourceError</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">page.reason</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">resourceError.errorString</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">page.reason_url</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">resourceError.url</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">var </span><span class="nv">fs</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">&#39;fs</span><span class="o">&#39;</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">var </span><span class="nv">sys</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">&#39;system</span><span class="o">&#39;</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">var </span><span class="nv">success</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">page.onConsoleMessage</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">function</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">var </span><span class="nv">line</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">x.toString</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">line</span> <span class="nv">!==</span> <span class="s">&quot;[NEWLINE]&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nv">sys.stdout.writeLine</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">line.replace</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">/</span><span class="sc">\[</span><span class="nv">NEWLINE</span><span class="sc">\]</span><span class="nv">/g</span>, <span class="s">&quot;\n&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">page.open</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">&#39;http://localhost:4500</span><span class="o">&#39;</span>, <span class="nv">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">status</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">status</span> <span class="nv">!==</span> <span class="s">&quot;success&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nv">console.log</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;Couldn&#39;t load page&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nv">phantom.exit</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">for </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">var </span><span class="nv">i</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="c1">; i &lt; sys.args.length; i++) {</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">fs.exists</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">sys.args</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">i</span><span class="p">]))</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">!page.injectJs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">sys.args</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">i</span><span class="p">]))</span> <span class="nv">throw</span> <span class="k">new </span><span class="nv">Error</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;Failed to inject &quot;</span> <span class="nb">+ </span><span class="nv">sys.args</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">i</span><span class="p">])</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">}</span> <span class="nv">else</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="nv">page.evaluateJavaScript</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;(function () { &quot;</span> <span class="nb">+ </span><span class="nv">sys.args</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="nb">+ </span><span class="s">&quot;;&quot;</span> <span class="nb">+ </span><span class="s">&quot; })&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">page.evaluate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">function</span> <span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nv">cemerick.cljs.test.set_print_fn_BANG_</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="nv">console.log</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">x.replace</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">/</span><span class="sc">\n</span><span class="nv">/g</span>, <span class="s">&quot;[NEWLINE]&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span><span class="c1">; // since console.log *itself* adds a newline</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="p">})</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">})</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">success</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">page.evaluate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">function</span> <span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">var </span><span class="nv">results</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">cemerick.cljs.test.run_all_tests</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nv">console.log</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">results</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nv">return</span> <span class="nv">cemerick.cljs.test.successful_QMARK_</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">results</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">})</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">phantom.exit</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">success</span> <span class="nv">?</span> <span class="mi">0</span> <span class="err">:</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">})</span><span class="c1">;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And a rake task to stand up a server and run everything. If you don&#8217;t
use Rails for your Javascript code you might need to use different
commands to compile, but the intention remains. The WEBrick server
provides a blank page for us to visit and run our tests on, which
prevents PhantomJS from raising security errors.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='clojure'><span class='line'><span class="nv">require</span> <span class="ss">&#39;fileutils</span><span class="o">&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">require</span> <span class="ss">&#39;webrick</span><span class="o">&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">namespace </span><span class="ss">:test</span> <span class="nv">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nv">desc</span> <span class="s">&quot;Run ClojureScript generative tests&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nv">task</span> <span class="ss">:generative</span> <span class="nv">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">server</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">WEBrick</span><span class="ss">::HTTPServer.new</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="ss">:Port</span> <span class="nv">=&gt;</span> <span class="mi">4500</span>, <span class="ss">:DocumentRoot</span> <span class="nv">=&gt;</span> <span class="s">&quot;.&quot;</span>, <span class="ss">:BindAddress</span> <span class="nv">=&gt;</span> <span class="s">&quot;0.0.0.0&quot;</span><span class="p">})</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">Thread.new</span> <span class="nv">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nv">server.start</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">exitCode</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="mi">0</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">begin</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nv">Rake</span><span class="ss">::Task</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="ss">&#39;assets:clean</span><span class="o">&#39;</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="nv">.invoke</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nv">Rake</span><span class="ss">::Task</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="ss">&#39;assets:precompile</span><span class="o">&#39;</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="nv">.invoke</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nv">exitCode</span> <span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">system</span> <span class="s">&quot;lein cljsbuild test&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">ensure</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nv">server.shutdown</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nv">exit</span> <span class="nv">exitCode</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nv">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>To make all this work together, update project.clj to reference the
generative_runner.js file instead of :runner, and use <code>rake
test:generative</code> to kick off the run.</p>

<h1>Don&#8217;t Mangle Your Code</h1>

<p>If your application is anything like Tracker, you might use some Google
Closure dependencies without using the entire Closure compiler. And even
if you don&#8217;t need use Closure, you certainly have functions and classes
in the global namespace that you don&#8217;t want mangled.</p>

<p>To get around this, I recommend the following settings:</p>

<p>Add <code>:libs [ "compiled-application.js" ""]</code> to the cljsbuild section
in project.clj. This prevents DoubleCheck compiler errors due to
classpath issues, and it allows the Closure compiler to see everything
that your application provides. So if your tests and applications have
overlapping Closure dependencies you won&#8217;t get double provide errors.</p>

<p>Secondly I recommend that you only use the simple compilation mode. This
will prevent Closure from mangling global names, which will make
debugging easier and prevent your tests from being able to find the
production code. The space saving and code elimination that advanced
mode provides is more of a problem than a benefit for testing, so it&#8217;s
not worth fighting to get advanced to work.</p>

<p>You can fiddle with source maps if you wish, but I
haven&#8217;t had much luck or use for them; simple compiled Clojurescript is
easy to read, and most of the serious errors have come from the 43k
application javascript file, not the test file.</p>

<h1>Have Fun and Make More Tests</h1>

<p>Once you have that going, it should be possible to open up and create
increasingly complicated tests. As a teaser and a good example, the
following code caught a tricky JS ordering bug.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='clojure'><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">ns </span><span class="nv">tracker-cljs.panel-items-test</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">:require</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clojure.test.check</span> <span class="ss">:as</span> <span class="nv">core</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clojure.test.check.generators</span> <span class="ss">:as</span> <span class="nv">gen</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clojure.test.check.properties</span> <span class="ss">:as</span> <span class="nv">prop</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">cemerick.cljs.test</span> <span class="ss">:as</span> <span class="nv">t</span><span class="p">])</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">:require-macros</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clojure.test.check.clojure-test</span> <span class="ss">:refer</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">defspec</span><span class="p">)]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                   <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clojure.test.check.properties</span> <span class="ss">:refer</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">for-all</span><span class="p">)]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                   <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">cemerick.cljs.test</span> <span class="ss">:refer</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">is</span><span class="p">)]))</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">defn </span><span class="nv">ids</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">items</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">(</span><span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">seq? </span><span class="nv">items</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">map </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">fn </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">item</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">.get</span> <span class="nv">item</span> <span class="ss">:id</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>         <span class="nv">items</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">map </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">fn </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">item</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">.get</span> <span class="nv">item</span> <span class="ss">:id</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>         <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">.-models</span> <span class="nv">items</span><span class="p">))))</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">defn </span><span class="nv">create-models</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">ids</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">map </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">fn </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">Backbone.Model.</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">js-obj</span> <span class="ss">:id</span> <span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">)))</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="nv">ids</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">defspec</span> <span class="nv">sort-check</span> <span class="mi">100</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">for-all</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">v</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">gen/such-that</span> <span class="nv">gen/not-empty</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">gen/vector</span> <span class="nv">gen/int</span><span class="p">))]</span>
</span><span class='line'>           <span class="p">(</span><span class="k">let </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">models</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">create-models</span> <span class="nv">v</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>                 <span class="nv">sorted</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">sort </span><span class="nv">v</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>                 <span class="nv">subject</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">tracker.PanelItems.</span><span class="p">)]</span>
</span><span class='line'>             <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">.reset</span> <span class="nv">subject</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">apply </span><span class="nv">array</span> <span class="nv">models</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>             <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">.refresh</span> <span class="nv">subject</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">apply </span><span class="nv">array</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">sort-by </span><span class="o">#</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">.get</span> <span class="nv">%</span> <span class="ss">:id</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="nv">models</span><span class="p">)))</span>
</span><span class='line'>             <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">is</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">= </span><span class="nv">sorted</span>
</span><span class='line'>                    <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">ids</span> <span class="nv">subject</span><span class="p">))))))</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And the following is our project.clj, with unnecessary details elided
for readability.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='clojure'><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">defproject </span><span class="nv">generative-testing</span> <span class="s">&quot;0.0.1-SNAPSHOT&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="ss">:plugins</span> <span class="p">[[</span><span class="nv">lein-cljsbuild</span> <span class="s">&quot;1.0.3&quot;</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">com.cemerick/clojurescript.test</span> <span class="s">&quot;0.2.2&quot;</span><span class="p">]]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="ss">:dependencies</span> <span class="p">[[</span><span class="nv">org.clojure/clojurescript</span> <span class="s">&quot;0.0-2234&quot;</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                 <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">com.cemerick/clojurescript.test</span> <span class="s">&quot;0.3.1&quot;</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                 <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">com.cemerick/double-check</span> <span class="s">&quot;0.5.8-SNAPSHOT&quot;</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                 <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">org.clojure/clojure</span> <span class="s">&quot;1.5.1&quot;</span><span class="p">]]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="ss">:cljsbuild</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="ss">:builds</span> <span class="p">[{</span><span class="ss">:source-paths</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="s">&quot;test/cljs&quot;</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                        <span class="ss">:compiler</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="ss">:output-to</span> <span class="s">&quot;tmp/tracker-cljs.js&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>                                   <span class="ss">:libs</span> <span class="p">[</span> <span class="s">&quot;public/web/assets/application.js&quot;</span> <span class="s">&quot;&quot;</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                                   <span class="ss">:optimizations</span> <span class="ss">:simple</span>
</span><span class='line'>                                   <span class="ss">:pretty-print</span> <span class="nv">true</span><span class="p">}}]</span>
</span><span class='line'>              <span class="ss">:test-commands</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="s">&quot;unit-tests&quot;</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="s">&quot;phantomjs&quot;</span> <span class="s">&quot;lib/generative_runner.js&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>                                            <span class="s">&quot;public/next/assets/next/next.js&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>                                            <span class="s">&quot;tmp/tracker-cljs.js&quot;</span><span class="p">]}})</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Also, the following function is helpful for converting from Cljs data
structures to pure Javascript ones. It causes some compiler warnings,
but they appear to be harmless.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='clojure'><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">defn </span><span class="nv">clj-&gt;js</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="s">&quot;Recursively transforms ClojureScript maps into Javascript objects,</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">   other ClojureScript colls into JavaScript arrays, and ClojureScript</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s">   keywords into JavaScript strings.&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">cond</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">string? </span><span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="nv">x</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">keyword? </span><span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">name </span><span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">map? </span><span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">apply </span><span class="nv">js-obj</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">flatten</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">map </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">fn </span><span class="p">[[</span><span class="nb">key </span><span class="nv">val</span><span class="p">]]</span> <span class="p">[(</span><span class="nf">clj-&gt;js</span> <span class="nv">key</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">clj-&gt;js</span> <span class="nv">val</span><span class="p">)])</span> <span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">)))</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">coll?</span> <span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">apply </span><span class="nv">array</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">map </span><span class="nv">clj-&gt;js</span> <span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="ss">:else</span> <span class="nv">x</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Good luck, and don&#8217;t hesitate to reach out to me on Twitter if you have
any questions!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unusual Productivity Hacks]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/06/19/unusual-productivity-hacks/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-19T07:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/06/19/unusual-productivity-hacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The internet is lousy with productivity ideas, mostly about how to work harder or longer. I personally believe that good productivity is about maximizing per hour results, not working harder. And the fastest way to improve your productivity is to eliminate some of the things slowing you down. So rather than going over the usual suspects, let&#8217;s take a look at eliminating some of the low hanging fruit.</p>

<h2>1. Conquer Your Diet.</h2>

<p>What you eat is the cornerstone of who you are and what you do. The proteins in your muscle, the fats in your cell walls and your brain, and the amino acids used throughout your body must all come from, or be synthesized from your food. Low quality food products like trans fats have been connected with apathy, depression, and might be related to ADD. In order for your brain and body to perform at peak levels you need to give it high quality food to repair and refuel.</p>

<h2>2. Sleep</h2>

<p>Sleep is massively underrated. Everyone knows at this point that Americans are typically not getting enough sleep on a nightly basis, but distressingly few people consider it to be an issue. After all, hours spent asleep aren&#8217;t hours spent working right? Unfortunately it isn&#8217;t that simple. Insufficient or low quality sleep is one of the fastest ways that we know of to destroy per hour productivity. Get sleep or waste your precious waking hours in a mind fog.</p>

<h2>3. Know when to stop.</h2>

<p>Athletes regularly destroy their bodies by &#8220;over training&#8221;; exercising to the point of injury or chronic fatigue. The results of over training are often slow growth or even frustrating setbacks despite hundreds of hours at the gym or on the track.</p>

<p>Mental workers regularly do the exact same thing to their mind by working well past the point of mental burnout. There is very little use in working when you are not going to be putting out at least average results, and you risk ruining your morale after hours of low-results work. Instead of ritualistically working even when you are spent gain an intuitive sense for when you will accomplish little and instead go recharge and try again later.</p>

<h2>4. You must come out unharmed 1 time or 1000 times.</h2>

<p>No productivity regime is worthwhile if you can only maintain it for 2 weeks at the start of each year. To be successful, you must find a pattern that you can maintain years. Whether that is a small amount per day or a cycle between intense work and relaxation, you must find a balance between work and play or you will be plagued by failures to meet your goals.</p>

<h2>5. Know thyself.</h2>

<p>Everyone wants to be successful, but most people overestimate how much money motivates them. Find ways to motivate yourself with something other than riches, or better yet find something that you love to do. Love of the work will make it easier to get up, or home, every day and work rather than abstract future financial rewards.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Swordsman and the Software Engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/06/09/the-swordsman-and-the-software-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-09T22:31:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/06/09/the-swordsman-and-the-software-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the largest mistakes you can make as a knowledge worker is to focus 100% of your time on your craft. It&#8217;s easy to believe that specializing and focusing will make you better than your peers, but I do not think that is the case. Not only will specializing cause you to plateau earlier than your peers, it will cause you to be less happy and healthy than your diversified peers.</p>

<p>A bit of background at this point would probably be helpful. I&#8217;m a software engineer and I&#8217;ve coded both professionally and on a hobbyist basis for nearly a decade. After a particularly stressful few months at a previous job, my fianc forced me to join a local gym to de-stress. The gym focused on various European martial arts and I ended up in a class for the Italian longsword circa 1409.</p>

<p>A few years ago I would have suspected that choosing to surrender 2-8 hours a week to swinging steel around instead of programming on hobbyist projects would slow down my growth. Now I believe that I owe a lot of my growth, professionally and as a human being to this practice. A lot of what I&#8217;m going to cover here will probably be old news to anyone who was heavily involved in sports, nor is it particularly unique to fencing. That being said I&#8217;m fairly confident that a lot of knowledge workers have lost the involvement with physical activities they might have had, or never were all that &#8220;athletic&#8221; even in school.</p>

<p>The biggest modern challenge is that humans are not wired for the type of work that we now do. We are a fairly clever species by nature, which is why we have been making art for hundreds of thousands of years. But we are still more or less genetically and mentally hunter gatherers from 100,000+ years ago who largely worked for their survival. Our bodies, genes, and minds are wired to expect a specific ratio of play and physical activity to signal that all is well. Unfortunately we work a lot longer than our ancestors did, and under very different conditions.</p>

<p>This high level of nothing but work, physical or mental, indicates to our bodies that times are tough and that it should release stress hormones to help us survive the coming hard times; these stress hormones tend to have serious detrimental effects on mental performance and long term health. The phrase &#8220;all work and no play&#8221; may be over-used, but it does have some truth. All work and no play leaves Jack pumped full of cortisol, short on sleep, and low on testosterone.</p>

<p>Secondly, most knowledge workers spend their entire time thinking only with their frontal cortex, or the analytical portion of the brain. This is very helpful if your job involves concentrating on difficult problems all day, but it is incredibly easy to let that portion of your brain become the only driving factor on your day to day life. The brain, like your muscles, should have ample opportunity to exercise all of its faculties and have recovery time between each heavy usage. Expecting it to be able to focus deeply on your work day in and day out without giving it time to relax is simply asking for lowered performance and burnout, and only working on one aspect of your mental performance is akin to only doing curls at the gym; the result is an odd shape with very little practical strength.</p>

<p>Thankfully exercise and hobbies help other parts of the brain. This is one of the things I love about fencing: it isn&#8217;t very analytical once you actually start using it. There are a ton of cuts and guards to be memorized, but you never have time to think about it when you are actually fencing. All of the drills are designed so that your mind and body learn to move with instinctual grace from one guard to another. There is very little conscious thought that happens mid-move in a match; there simply is not enough time to stop and think. Instead you learn to have an internalized notion of time and measure, and an ability to make new decisions as the fight progresses quickly and correctly.</p>

<p>And while none of this directly relates to software engineering, it has a positive effect on my daily work. The ability to move with a fight and think with my toes and fingertips have given me a greater appreciation to the importance of gut instinct in more situations. And the constant practice of excluding my analytical mind in a fast moving match have improved my ability to enter a flow state more easily. Combine these things with the general good effects of mental down time and exercise, and I think it&#8217;s hard to argue that my time would have been better spent working on hobbyist projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Confessions of a Language Snob]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/05/28/confessions-of-a-language-snob/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-28T22:29:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/05/28/confessions-of-a-language-snob</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am a language snob. In particular I fall head over heels for most functional languages, especially MLs and Lisps. Show me the latest and greatest Javascript framework and I will just wish I had immutable data types and a saner method dispatch system. I try to keep quiet about it at work with varying degrees of success, but it&#8217;s frustrating to work around one language&#8217;s problems when you know of other solutions.</p>

<p>The difficult reality that few admit is that every language has a weak point. Ruby is slow and the lack of import semantics and proper namespaces makes it difficult to determine what code will run. Python lacks a good lambda and whitespace sensitivity brings new difficulties. Javascript is just pure insanity. Lisp is poorly standardized and tends to have subpar documentation. The list goes on and on. No language is perfect, but it&#8217;s very easy to focus on the high points of one language while working through the low points of another.</p>

<p>The real bummer about being a language snob is that there&#8217;s really nothing to be done about it. For any given issue there will always be another language that exceeds in that area, but it&#8217;s almost always insane and impractical to convert your entire company over to it. So even if you think Go would solve every problem that your Python codebase has, and you know that the downsides wouldn&#8217;t be insurmountable, the simple reality is that convincing the organization to throw away their perfectly good Python code on a whim is insane at best. And that&#8217;s assuming that converting to your language wouldn&#8217;t come with downsides worse than the language you are coming from.</p>

<p>Thankfully, there is an upside to being a language snob. Polyglots have a far more flexible understanding of what a program should do, especially when they&#8217;re used to a wide range of paradigms. Someone who has done nothing but C or Java programming might have very little context into why mutable state can be so problematic, but someone who knows Clojure or Haskell will know the tradeoffs of mutable vs. immutable state intimately. Each new paradigm a programmer embraces means that they have more internal views on how a particular problem could be solved, a bit like having an experienced team in your head to discuss the merits of various techniques at lightning speed.</p>

<p>While it may be very frustrating to know of better solutions in other languages, there is a benefit to knowing about them. Being a language snob can help you evaluate your choices more effectively and discover solutions and strategies that might not be immediately obvious if you only knew one language. And between being a bit of a snob and attempting to shoe-horn every problem into a one-size fits all paradigm, I&#8217;ll take being a snob.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Primacy of the Build Tool]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/03/31/the-primacy-of-the-build-tool/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-31T13:55:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/03/31/the-primacy-of-the-build-tool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No programming language stands alone. Besides the compiler, every
programming language includes an ecosystem of libraries, build tools,
analyzers, debuggers, and other utilities. Languages often rise and fall
depending on the quality of these tools and libraries.</p>

<p>For every language there needs to be one central item upon which every
other tool depends. In most languages, this is the compiler or
interpreter. Your Rails project is entirely dependent on the version of
Ruby provided by the current environment, and similarly Maven depends on
the version of javac and java available on the path.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this makes our code more fragile and dependent on the
machine it was first created on. Someone cloning your code from a
different machine must take care to ensure that their development
environment is close to the original authors, and deployment must ship
the correct compilers and interpeters for production to work well. We
have created tools to help enforce the requirements of the code, but
they are fragile and make upgrading dependencies a pain, as anyone who
has had to fight with RVM can attest.</p>

<p>The one exception to this I have found is Clojure. Clojure inverts the
normal order making the build tool the central item, with the compiler
provided by the project definition file.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='clojure'><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">defproject </span><span class="nv">foo</span> <span class="s">&quot;0.1.0-SNAPSHOT&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="ss">:description</span> <span class="s">&quot;FIXME: write description&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="ss">:url</span> <span class="s">&quot;http://example.com/FIXME&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="ss">:license</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="ss">:name</span> <span class="s">&quot;All Rights Reserved.&quot;</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="ss">:dependencies</span> <span class="p">[[</span><span class="nv">org.clojure/clojure</span> <span class="s">&quot;1.5.1&quot;</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                 <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">org.clojure/clojure-contrib</span> <span class="s">&quot;1.2.0&quot;</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>                 <span class="p">[</span><span class="nv">clj-time</span> <span class="s">&quot;0.6.0&quot;</span><span class="p">]]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="ss">:profiles</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="ss">:dev</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="ss">:dependencies</span> <span class="p">[[</span><span class="nv">midje</span> <span class="s">&quot;1.5.1&quot;</span><span class="p">]]}})</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The beauty of this change is that it makes setup trivial for another
developer. All they need is the same build tool, and it will deal with
the correct versions of both the compiler and any libraries for the
project. Have other projects that depend on different versions of the
compiler? The build tool only cares about the dependencies in front of
it, and will call the correct version from the correct project.</p>

<p>This also makes upgrading trivial. Want to try Clojure 1.6.0? Change
&#8220;1.5.1&#8221; to &#8220;1.6.0&#8221; in the above snippet. Want to write a library that
supports multiple versions of the compiler? The build tool supports
profiles which allow you to swap out compilers trivially because it&#8217;s
just a dependency.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='clojure'><span class='line'><span class="ss">:profiles</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="ss">:1.3</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="ss">:dependencies</span> <span class="p">[[</span><span class="nv">org.clojure/clojure</span> <span class="s">&quot;1.3.0&quot;</span><span class="p">]]}</span>
</span><span class='line'>           <span class="ss">:1.4</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="ss">:dependencies</span> <span class="p">[[</span><span class="nv">org.clojure/clojure</span> <span class="s">&quot;1.4.0-beta1&quot;</span><span class="p">]]}}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Deployment gets easier as well. If you&#8217;re deploying an uberjar, the core
libraries you tested against are also shipped to production in the same
jar. No need to upgrade your deployment scripts when a new version of
Clojure comes out, as everything is included automatically.</p>

<p>There is one catch to this wonderfulness, which is that Clojure depends
on the JVM, and the build tool cannot change the JVM around. But Clojure
has very simple requirements, Java 1.6 or greater, which
makes it simple to deploy anywhere.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Disdain]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/03/24/disdain/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-24T20:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/03/24/disdain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of my hobbies is fencing. Not modern Olympic fencing, but 14th
century longsword fencing in the Italian school. In every class the
instructor reminds us that we should act &#8220;like haughty Italian nobles,
tall and relaxed&#8221; in the way that we stand, move, and handle the weapon.</p>

<p>The word &#8220;Sprezzatura&#8221; crops up a lot in these discussions. The simplest
translation is literally &#8220;disdain&#8221;, but a more careful translation would
be &#8220;studied carelessness&#8221;. To act with Sprezzatura means to make learned
actions look easy and natural.</p>

<p>It turns out there is a really good reason for a fencer to act this
way. A relaxed and calm fencer can move more rapidly and adjust their
actions depending on whether they are winning or losing the bind. Their
actions happen without any tell, catching their opponent by surprise and
allowing them to act within their opponents tempo. In sword fighting the
ultimate goal is to strike your opponent without being hit. Thus the
shortest and simplest actions are favored, as large embellished actions
only increase personal risk.</p>

<p>There is a similar grace in programming. While programming is not
usually a competitive or dangerous hobby, there are practical benefits
to acting quickly and gracefully. The most effective engineer completes
their task with the minimal amount of time and added complexity. Showing
off in the code only increases the risk of regressions and makes the
code harder to modify later. The ultimate goal is a maintainable
application that meets requirements in the minimal amount of time, and
an accomplished engineer will take the shortest route to that goal.</p>

<p>Sword fighting is not about strength. It is never effective to swing a
sword with all of your strength. Even if this wasn&#8217;t unsafe and an
obvious tell, it isn&#8217;t a good way to cut with an edged weapon. Swords
depend on a cutting edge to do damage, and thus a smooth arc that draws
the weapon through the target will always cut more effectively than a
ham-fisted baseball swing.</p>

<p>Similarly, the accomplished engineer knows that completing a task is not
about the number of hours spent, but the quality. The mind is a tool
that can be both sharpened and dulled with both work and rest, and
programming is a task of the mind. Thus the quality engineer avoids
excessive hours, as they are unhealthy and ineffective. Instead the
engineer makes their limited productive hours as effective as possible
without excessive strain.</p>

<p>It may not be the connection you expected, but humans haven&#8217;t changed in
a very long time. Even if our circumstances have changed, there is
always something to be learned from even the most esoteric sources.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing is a Craft Too]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/01/14/managing-is-a-craft-too/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-14T22:45:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/01/14/managing-is-a-craft-too</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m getting a little tired of seeing posts saying that the best managers
must be an ex-engineer or a current one. I think coding skill is a very
narrow minded way to judge both a human and a professional, and a
terrible way to run a business.</p>

<p>Here&#8217;s the simple truth, a manager is a craftsperson just like a
designer or engineer. The only difference is that their craft is
organizing people, not designs or code. In their trade the best tools
are flexibility, communication, empathy, and comprehension. My personal
opinion is that a good manager is at least as hard to find as a good
engineer, if not harder.</p>

<p>To say that a manager of engineers needs to know how code and needs to
code daily is like saying that you have to be a doctor to manage a
doctor&#8217;s office, and that you need to be practicing right now. While a
bit of knowledge aids in communication, there are a wide range of tasks
that need to be performed that are <em>not</em> coding. And to ignore these
tasks would be just as disastrous as not writing the software that the
company sells.</p>

<p>We&#8217;ve all heard the horror stories of non-engineer managers not knowing
or caring what engineers do, or the ex-engineer manager thinking that
they&#8217;re still on the team when their knowledge is 20 years out of
date. Clearly both of these people are being ineffective managers, but
not because of whether or not they can code. These people are being bad
managers because they are not <em>listening</em> to their staff. Anyone, coder
or not, will be a terrible manager without the requisite people skills.</p>

<p>So hire and keep managers that listen and communicate well. Managers
that manage expectations of those uphill and divert shit rolling
downhill. The best manager is the one that helps their team be the best,
whether or not there are any commits with their name on it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Internationalization Golf]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/01/06/internationalization-golf/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-06T22:48:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/01/06/internationalization-golf</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Martin Grner had a <a href="http://martingryner.com/software-localization-is-tricky/">fun</a> article about his experience writing an internationalized app. I thought it would be fun to share my own experiences.</p>

<p>My first job out of college was working on a Common Lisp (CL) web application. The application was only a few years younger than me, and had originally written in CL due to a particularly good HTML/XML library available in CL at the time. Unfortunately in the intervening years the HTML library stopped being state of the art, and the whims of enterprise software engineering had left CL behind for web development, resulting in a serious lack of common programming conveniences.</p>

<p>Right after joining the company, I was informed that the sales person had a potential lead with clients in a Spanish speaking country. The application at this point was English only, but the QA engineer was married to a native Spanish speaker who was willing to help translate the application. All we needed to do was wire the application up for internationalization and localization. I was tasked with picking or creating a library and interspersing it throughout the application. The only criteria was that it both looked good and was capable of displaying different languages to different users depending on their browser&#8217;s &#8220;accept-language&#8221; header. So compiling or packaging up a new application with hard-coded languages was not an option.</p>

<p>I eventually decided that all the existing libraries were insufficient and we needed to make our own. I&#8217;m still not sure if that was the right choice or not. CL doesn&#8217;t have the strongest library ecosystem around, but I was also a very young engineer and more susceptible to the &#8220;Not Invented Here&#8221; syndrome than I am now. Although a quick perusal through the current offerings involves libraries whose home pages are 404s, libraries who are nothing but FFI bindings to a GNU C library, and those whose list of defects includes &#8220;no documentation&#8221;, &#8220;undocumented code&#8221; and &#8220;slow PO parser&#8221;.</p>

<p>Compounding the issue was CL&#8217;s format function. CL has an exceedingly powerful formatter that is capable of unwrapping loops and interspersing the correct combination of &#8220;,&#8221; and &#8220;and&#8221; for a list of strings. This function was used with (reckless) abandon throughout the codebase, something for which I deserve some blame. The lack of dedicated template files compounded the issues; it&#8217;s a lot easier to reach for format when you&#8217;re producing HTML the handler-function itself.</p>

<p>There was no way I was going to explain the (non-technical) translator how to deal with format directives like this: &#8220;~#[NONE~;~a~;~a and ~a~:;~a, ~a~]~#[~; and ~a~:;, ~a, etc~].&#8221;, and I didn&#8217;t want to dig through 500kloc and unroll all the directives. So any translation system I made would need to support at least a subset of the CL formatting directives while hiding them for the translator&#8217;s sanity.</p>

<p>Worse still, CL&#8217;s formatter accepts positional arguments only, to my knowledge. Thus there&#8217;s no particular way to convince the formatter to modify the order of the parameters if the target language has different language structure than English. So my system would need to deal with that.</p>

<p>The final format I settled on would look something like this. The programmer (me) would change (format nil &#8220;~a&#8221; var) to (jibberish:format &#8220;&lt;~a:variable-name&gt;&#8221; &#8220;Descriptive sentence for translator&#8221; :variable-name var). We could then convince our code to print out a file for a language like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>####################################
</span><span class='line'>File: filename.cl
</span><span class='line'>####################################
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Original: &lt;variable-name&gt;
</span><span class='line'>Translation: Translation goes here
</span><span class='line'>Note for translator: Descriptive sentence for translator
</span><span class='line'>Original Argument Order: [variable-name]</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And so on. At runtime the language file would be parsed into a in-memory hash map, which would allow us to replace the format-string with the new one, re-order the argument list according to the translator&#8217;s needs, and strip the identifiers from the formatting string leaving the raw format directives.</p>

<p>So, how&#8217;d I do? Mixed results. The conversion was long and painful, requiring that each format directive and raw string be touched. A huge portion of the &#8220;Notes for translator&#8221; were either blank due to difficulty and fatigue, or were something along the line &#8220;Description, part 1/n&#8221; due to multiple calls being joined together in HTML. Changes in formatting calls required that the matching translation entry be hunted down <em>in every translation file</em> for the translation to still work.</p>

<p>But technical challenges are usually not a big deal, after all that&#8217;s a fairly large portion of what engineers do. Probably the worst problem with my system was how it worked for non-technical folk. The first attempt at giving this file to a translator resulted in her helpfully translating all the variable names into spanish, changing &#8220;It is &lt;today&gt;&#8221; to &#8220;que es &lt;hoy&gt;&#8221;, which resulted in some rather exciting errors. I think my own design sabotaged me in this particular instance, as it required way too much careful explanation to be usable. It was my first encounter with the major difference between using a program whose internals you are familiar and explaining its use to someone else who has never seen anything similar.</p>

<p>I think if I had to do it again, I would&#8217;ve probably spent more time and modified the way the program generated strings instead. I suspect that my custom library avoiding refactoring everything was a case of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_economy">false economy</a>, as the time saved up front would have been lost in the time required to train translators and maintain overly fragile translation files. I also learned that if you plan on selling an application in another language market, you need to think about that <em>before</em> you start writing code. Internationalization limits some of the choices you can make with your software and design, and it&#8217;s a lot easier to use that restricted set up front than it is to unwind them after the fact.</p>

<p>As a final irony, while attempting to write this post in Octopress (which uses Jekyll), it crashed several times because the SASS files in Octopress use unicode, which Octopress appears to hate out of the box. You have to change a few environment variables to convince it that Unicode is ok.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on RubyMine]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/12/20/thoughts-on-rubymine/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-20T21:38:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/12/20/thoughts-on-rubymine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of my new job at Pivotal Labs I&#8217;ve been pair programming almost
every day. The obvious challenge with pair programming, especially in a
popular language like ruby, is in choosing what tools to work with. Vim,
Emacs, RubyMine, TextMate, the choices are various and divisive.</p>

<p>To make peace among the engineers, it makes sense to dictate one set of
tools to make peace among all your employees, and to make provisioning
the machines easier. Pivotal has decided to standardize on RubyMine with
a dark color scheme and a few custom configurations.</p>

<h1>The Good</h1>

<p>RubyMine, being set up for ruby in particular, works very well with
navigating, indenting, and colorizing ruby code. With the exception of
setting a variable as the result of an if expression, I have never seen
RubyMine indent code incorrectly or get confused on coloration.</p>

<p>It also does a decent job of navigating to ruby classes and functions,
something that is quite hard since ruby lacks explicit import
semantics. It definitely makes hunting down odd test harness functions
down a breeze, and has saved me in the past. It also is good at
identifying the view that cooresponds to a controller method, but due to
the way that tracker is laid out, I haven&#8217;t had a chance to use this
feature often.</p>

<p>And as the cherry on top RubyMine includes a &#8220;Textmate like&#8221; quick find
feature. In large code bases this will save you about a minute trying to
find a particular file, so ling as you have an idea of what it&#8217;s called!</p>

<h1>The Bad</h1>

<p>If you only have unique controllers and models, you will absolutely love
the ability to jump to a class definition. Since we use a lot of
similarly named controllers inside namespaces to control API versions,
it often gets confused about what version I want. The quick find feature
sometimes ignores the path if you provide it, which makes copying files
from stacktraces occasionally unreliable.</p>

<p>Javascript and less support is mediocre. No real complaints, but nothing
to set it apart from other environments in my opinion. Maybe my
colleagues who work on the front end would have a more nuanced opinion.</p>

<p>Also sometimes with large files the coloring or error checking can lag
behind. This usually kicks in at files longer than 3000 lines, which is
not unusual for test files. For the most part this is just an annoyance
which doesn&#8217;t affect editing in any serious way.</p>

<p>It has git integration, which lags behind the offerings from Emacs, Vim,
and Eclipse in my opinion. I end up using the command line instead of
the built in tools.</p>

<h1>The Ugly</h1>

<p>RubyMine is incredibly dim witted when it comes to parenthesis and
quotes. If you wish to put an escaped quote at the end of a string,
RubyMine will let you escape your ending quote, then insert a matching
pair right afterwords when you try and fix the mistake! To add insult to
injury, you must move the cursor before fixing the issue lest RubyMine
delete both of the extra quotes. Very frustrating.</p>

<p>RubyMine is also one of the most memory consuming programs I use. At
least once a week it will grind my machine to a halt due to memory
usage, which is impressive on a machine with 16G in memory.</p>

<h1>Conclusions</h1>

<p>Out of the box, RubyMine works very well. I think it is a good
compromise for large teams. But if you have time to learn some more
complicated tools, I believe you would be way better off learning a more
customizable editor like Emacs or Vim. It might take some effort, but
these editors can do just as much as their commercial cousins and will
continue to do well no matter what language you decide to use in the
future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Org Mode]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/11/04/org-mode/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-04T18:55:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/11/04/org-mode</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I&#8217;ve taken interest in making myself more productive, and at
least so far it&#8217;s going well. I personally attribute part of my current
productivity to a new &#8220;shut up and get back to work&#8221; mentality, and
partly to a new (to me) organization system.</p>

<p>The problem I&#8217;ve had is that every single organization app is broken in
some way. The only truly flexible system uses paper and pen, and I
don&#8217;t really want to deal with that.</p>

<p>The solution appears to be org-files. Think of them as a close cousin to
Markdown, but for organization instead of HTML. The systems that use
org-files support basically any kind of work flow imaginable because
the storage mechanism is just text, so in the worst case scenario you
can always just edit the file manually.</p>

<p>Org-files are originally from the Emacs plugin org-mode, but there are
now org-file readers for Vim, iPhone, and Android.</p>

<h2>Example File.</h2>

<pre>
#+LAST_MOBILE_CHANGE: 2013-10-01 19:59:54
#+TODO: TODO IN-PROGRESS DONE


* Butler                                                           :projects:
Butler is an Emacs plugin for Jenkins/Hudson use. Currently it supports:
+ Viewing jobs.
+ Encrypted authentication info.
+ Triggering non-parameterized jobs.
** Wish List.
*** Paramtererized jobs
Possible to get the parameter information along with the job status in one query.
*** DONE Better formatting.
DEADLINE: <2013-11-02 Sat>
CLOCK: [2013-05-06 Mon 20:21]--[2013-05-06 Mon 20:40] =>  0:19
:PROPERTIES:
:ID:       6A634BFA-F18E-4C92-A48D-DC3254A67CAE
:END:
Tabular mode?
*** DONE COMPLETED Job Progress
*** TODO Improved HTTP
:PROPERTIES:
:ORDERED:  t
:ID:       F720BD2F-4966-455B-8F14-5530393340CD
:END:
**** DONE Avoid roundtrip to encrypted auth file
**** TODO Silence message output
:PROPERTIES:
:ID:       DE9913E9-AC68-42D3-B7D2-613BB775A16B
:END:
**** TODO Auto refresh
 :PROPERTIES:
:ID:       01EC3DB8-ABCA-4063-8999-AA68D8D05528
:END:
**** TODO Console output
:PROPERTIES:
:ID:       112F3FD6-7D23-485F-8B5E-43F0B0BA839E
:END:
</pre>


<h2>Okay Ashton, What the Hell is That?</h2>

<p>Let&#8217;s break this down bit by bit. Any line starting with <code>#+</code>
is used to tell the org-mode reader something. In this case it lets us
know the last time we synced this to our mobile device, and the possible
TODO states that an item can be in. It&#8217;s not unusual to see formatting
directives at the top of the file to control color, indentation, and
similar settings. A lot of settings can either be set globally, or on a
per-file basis.</p>

<p>Next we have the individual headings. Each heading starts with a number
of asterisks. The number of asterisks indicates the level. So
<code>&#42;&#42; Wish List.</code> is a child of <code>&#42;
Butler</code>. Most editors allow you to fold headings to show or hide
their children, for convenience.</p>

<p>Each heading can optionally have a TODO state, which is displayed in
front of the heading title.. The default is one of blank, TODO,
IN-PROGRESS, and DONE. A simple keystroke in most editors cycles from
one state to the next. It&#8217;s also possible to support multiple paths that
a project can flow through. I personally use the default along with
REFERENCE and ABANDONED, which allows for me to easily filter for
abandoned projects, along with notes that aren&#8217;t actionable yet.</p>

<p>Org-mode supports 3 different kinds of time tracking and
scheduling. Each heading can have up to one deadline entry, one
scheduled entry, and multiple clock entries. Deadlines are for when an
item should be finished, and scheduled is for when a project should be
started. Clocks are for recording the amount of time used for an
item. You can see an example of both the deadline and clock under the
&#8220;Better formatting.&#8221;  header. Org-mode also supports a very flexible
type of repeat scheduling.</p>

<p>With any good organization system you&#8217;ll need the ability to tag and
filter items. Org provides two ways to do this, properties and
tags. Tags are generally shared across multiple entries, with values
like &#8220;work&#8221; and &#8220;home&#8221;. They are displayed on the far right of the
tagged line, such as &#8220;:projects:&#8221; on the Butler line above. You can tag
a line with as many tags as you want.</p>

<p>Unlike tags, properties are composed of keys and values, many of which
are unique to a specific entry. If you use any kind of syncing system,
each item will get an ID property used to enforce uniqueness. A lot of
systems will also respect the LOCATION property if you sync to a system
that understands this, such as iCal.</p>

<p>And finally you can have notes and text underneath each entry. Most
org-mode readers understand free text, unordered lists (<code>-</code>
or <code>+</code>), numbered lists, and check boxes (<code>- [ ]</code>
and <code>- [X]</code>). Many of these can be easily manipulated with
simple keyboard macros, such as the check boxes.</p>

<p>As you can see, org-mode basically provides a super set of all the
organizational features available. It&#8217;s up to you how you wish to nest
these, mark them due, and prioritize. That&#8217;s why I love it, I&#8217;m not
locked into one particular layout that may or may not fit me, instead I
can slowly evolve it as my systems mature. Expect more posts in the
future about Emacs specific configuration settings to make org-mode
easier to use.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best of Lisp]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/11/01/the-best-of-lisp/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T20:04:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/11/01/the-best-of-lisp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Edit: Dan Benjamin himself informed me that I missed the sarcasm boat
here. I&#8217;m leaving the relevant bits, and cutting out the now irrelevant
criticism.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m slowly working my way through the <a href="http://5by5.tv/b2w">Back to Work</a>
podcast. I&#8217;m way behind, so please excuse that this post references an
episode over 2 years old at this point.</p>

<p><a href="http://5by5.tv/b2w/11">Episode 11</a> was about &#8220;future proofing your
passion&#8221;, among other things. In it, Merlin mentions that one thing you
can do as a low risk investment in a programming career is to maintain
current on new languages. He mentions Scala, Erlang, and Lisp as a
few. With an <del>uncharacteristic lack of self-awareness</del> unusual
amount of sarcasm, Dan expresses pretty much disdain and lack of
interest in anything other than Ruby, even going as far as saying &#8220;Ruby
took the best of Lisp&#8221;.</p>

<p>While Dan may have been joking, it is probably worth examining the
relationship between Ruby and Lisp. As someone who has worked in Ruby
and Lisp professionally, I feel uniquely qualified to talk about their
relative strengths. While there are a ton of cases where Ruby clearly
learned and copied from Lisp, there is also a laundry list of areas
where Ruby failed to learn from Lisp&#8217;s successes and failures.</p>

<h2>Functions</h2>

<p>Being a functional language, functions are pretty important to Common
Lisp. Ruby thankfully took some of the highlights from CL during its
development, like a heavy emphasis on using map &amp; filter over iterative
loops, but it missed some important things.</p>

<p>CL only has one kind of function, the function. There are some nice
syntax features for the way you define them, and a few extra features
for how they&#8217;re called, but they&#8217;re all just functions. Some might be
anonymous, while others might be bound to a symbol. Sometimes you call
them by name, or with funcall or apply if you need to pass them
around. Sometimes they&#8217;re a multimethod from CLOS which dispatches
depending on the class of the argument, but at the end of the day
they&#8217;re all just functions which behave the same. Ruby picked up on the
idea of using different syntax for some functions (think Blocks), but
for some reason included Procs and Lambdas as well. Most Rubyists I&#8217;ve
met express confusion over what the exact differences are, and always
say &#8220;Just use one kind and one kind only&#8221;.</p>

<p>Common Lisp also has much better syntax for parameters. In particular it
provides for required and optional positional parameters, enumerated
keyword parameters, and extra parameters to be collected into a
list. Ruby learned well by also allowing default parameters to be
evaluated at call time, but it ended up with a way worse
syntax. Particularly bad is the way Ruby handles extra keyword
arguments, simply dumping them into a lisp, optionally merging it on top
of your default arguments hash if needed. CL provides a way for default
values to be defined for keyword arguments in the method header, which
is far cleaner than the Ruby way.</p>

<h2>DSLs</h2>

<p>Ruby often gets compared to Common Lisp in its ability to produce Domain
Specific Languages, or DSLs. Both blocks and Ruby&#8217;s special dispatch
mechanisms are used and abused by programs such as Chef to create an
easy interface between high level concepts and low level details.</p>

<p>And Ruby is pretty good at DSLs, I would estimate that it can hit a good
60-80% of the DSL cases fairly easily. But especially once you step
outside the bounds of configuration DSLs like Chef, Common Lisp truly
shines. In Ruby you can&#8217;t really add new syntax or special characters,
and you can&#8217;t easily force it to recompile a given section of code to
behave in a specific way.</p>

<p>But you can do that in Lisp. Lisp&#8217;s macros are so powerful, many
languages are first prototyped as a large section of Lisp
macros. Clojure was originally implemented in a few hundred lines of
Lisp macros. This involved adding new meanings to symbols that don&#8217;t
exist in CL, like { and }. But with Lisp&#8217;s reader and regular macros,
this is perfectly reasonable.</p>

<h2>Fragmentation</h2>

<p>One of the biggest weaknesses of Common Lisp was its weak standard. The
standard did not specify a lot of common behavior, such as
threading. The result was a proliferation of both libraries that were
implementation specific, and libraries designed to bridge the gap, like
<a href="http://common-lisp.net/project/bordeaux-threads/">Bordeaux Threads</a>. At
this point every library and application is so set in its ways, the
chances of the standard being unified and fixed is almost none.</p>

<p>Yet somehow Ruby ended up with no spec at all, only a reference
implementation. It&#8217;s so bad that the Rubinius people proudly proclaim
that they created 20,000 specifications to as closely as possible match
MRI, the reference implementation.  While this is a laudable effort, I
think the general opinion is that only the reference implementation is
to be trusted, so most libraries assume that you&#8217;re not using Rubinius,
MacRuby, or anything else. This is sad, because it means that the Ruby
community is very unlikely to use anything other than MRI, no matter how
good a competing runtime might be.</p>

<h2>The Takeaway</h2>

<p>I love Ruby. It&#8217;s a good language. But if you want truly mind opening
programming moments, Lisp is the only way to go. No other language can
give you the sense of &#8220;I can do <em>anything</em>&#8221; quite like it. I highly
recommend every Rubyist at least try Common Lisp for a bit, to at least
understand where their language of choice came from.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advanced Fear]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/10/30/advanced-existential-dread/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T19:50:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/10/30/advanced-existential-dread</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most scary moments in most young adults&#8217; life is the
realization of mortality. Teenagers and younger children often
understand on an intellectual level that people die, but emotionally
that&#8217;s something that happens to other people. There&#8217;s very few things
quite like the moment when an adult realizes that they must die, there&#8217;s
nothing they can do to stop it, and there&#8217;s not a lot they can do to
delay it.</p>

<p>Most people stop there. But if you move beyond the &#8220;go to work, make
money, enjoy weekend&#8221; stage of your life, you&#8217;ll get to experience what
I call &#8220;Opportunity Cost Fear&#8221;.</p>

<p>Every action you take prevents you from taking another. Spending $10 on
a lunch means you can&#8217;t spend that $10 on anything else. This is called
opportunity cost. It applies to every limited resource in the
world. Your time, attention, money, emotions, energy, and physical
strength are all subject to opportunity cost, even though many people
and organizations do not think about it.</p>

<p>Those who wish to accomplish many things can suffer a crippling fear
because of it. Spending time on this blog post means I&#8217;m spending time
not reading blogs, writing software, or talking with Leah. It also means
I&#8217;m not spending my time going to the gym to be healthy, or trying to
make friends in a new city. And the fact that I can&#8217;t have everything I
want, just like the fact that I can&#8217;t live forever, can be deeply
terrifying if you care about doing multiple things.</p>

<p>Just like the fear of death, the best way out of opportunity cost fear
is to press forward. The big risk with both is that the fear will
cripple you to the point where the worst might as well have
happened. Are you really living if you spend every moment terrified of
your own end? What&#8217;s the point worrying about opportunity cost if the
fear prevents you from executing on any of your plans? In both these
cases, the fear alone can be just as bad as the actual outcome.</p>

<p>Now, I&#8217;m not saying that the rational choice is disregard for the
objects of your fear. If you&#8217;re afraid of death, riding a motorcycle
without a helmet on will neither eliminate your fear or increase your
lifespan. You should be aware of why you feared a thing, and take the
most rational steps to reduce it. Nothing you will do can ever eliminate
opportunity cost, but you can make sure that you&#8217;re spending your time
as best you can. You&#8217;ll never do it perfectly, but it&#8217;s better than
nothing at all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Time, Attention, and Pairing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/10/26/time-attention-and-pairing/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-26T21:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/10/26/time-attention-and-pairing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.merlinmann.com">Merlin Mann</a> gives a great talk about Time
and Attention. The gist of his talk is that in order to create great
work, you need to balance time vs. attention. Without using your time,
you&#8217;ll never create. But you must use your attention to determine if
you&#8217;re creating something great. Great producers balance between these
two to both produce, and produce good work.</p>

<p>Part of my new job at <a href="http://www.pivotaltracker.com">Pivotal Tracker</a>
involves pair programming. While a lot of my programming friends express
doubt about pairing, I&#8217;m very impressed with both how productive I am
pairing, and how quickly I&#8217;m learning the code base while pairing.</p>

<p>The way that a good pair switches between who is &#8220;driving&#8221; is very
similar to Merlin&#8217;s talk. The person who is typing is responsible for
producing, while the person who isn&#8217;t is responsible for ensuring that
the pair is headed in the right direction. Pairs have a much easier time
finding this balance and staying on track than individual workers do.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s hard to alternate between time and attention effectively when
working alone. There&#8217;s no overt signal to when one is using time or
attention, making it easy to mistake &#8220;research&#8221; (reading Wikipedia) as
using your attention. As a pair this balance is much easier to achieve,
because each member is tasked with one role, and it&#8217;s obvious when that
role is not being fulfilled. The non-driving member can&#8217;t goof off on
Reddit or Wikipedia for the sake of &#8220;research&#8221; because it will prevent
the driving member from working. And the driving member can&#8217;t slow down
too much without the other member taking over typing from them. This
helps ensure that the pair produces better code faster.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m not sure if the creators of pair programming are familiar with
Merlin&#8217;s model of work, but accidentally or not they&#8217;ve made it much
easier for programmers to follow his advice. I&#8217;d recommend any
company to give pairing a try and see what it does for the quality and
quantity of work that their teams produce.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving to Denver]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/10/25/moving-to-denver/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T21:28:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/10/25/moving-to-denver</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You know those hilarious &#8220;pranks&#8221; where someone posts something
embarrassing someone else&#8217;s Facebook account? Apparently in the improv
community of Chicago the standard prank is to post something saying that
they&#8217;ve accepted a lead role, and that they&#8217;re moving to Denver,
Colorado. We found this out when some improv actors at our going away
party took some convincing that we were actually moving, and that it
wasn&#8217;t an elaborate prank.</p>

<p>The main difference for us is that I&#8217;ve not decided to give up software
engineering for comedy. Instead I&#8217;ve accepted a role as an engineer at
<a href="http://www.pivotaltracker.com">Pivotal Tracker</a>, which I personally think is a
better deal. Pivotal is a great company with a unique and productive
style, and I&#8217;m thrilled to be working with them.</p>

<p>While there&#8217;ll always be a special place in my heart for Chicago, I&#8217;m
rather glad we&#8217;ve made the move. It was stressful and very expensive,
but living in Colorado has already been a very pleasant experience. The
weather is shockingly nice, apartments are a nicer for the price, and I
can safely walk to work.</p>

<p>Expect photos from the mountains and trails above Denver in the coming
months.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Dangers of Partisanship]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/07/15/the-dangers-of-partisanship/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-15T21:01:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/07/15/the-dangers-of-partisanship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Anyone who knows me personally knows that I am a huge Clojure fan. I could go on and on about why it&#8217;s the best; the regularity, the macros, ClojureScript, core.logic, etc. etc.</p>

<p>But last week I attended <a href="http://lambdajam.com">LambdaJam</a>, which was awesome by the way, and I came back with a different opinion. No, I don&#8217;t think Haskell or Erlang tops out Clojure, I&#8217;m still probably going to reach for Leiningen for all my personal projects. But I learned that it&#8217;s a good idea to keep an eye on other languages, since no language will ever be so good that you never need to touch anything else.</p>

<p>In particular I learned the joy of the APL based languages, especially J. I learned that the F# people have a novel way of dealing with statically typing external resources via type providers, and I learned that Haskell can indeed be tight and clean despite what all those monad tutorials imply. I will probably take each of these subjects apart in separate posts in the future, I&#8217;m still trying to pick up bits and pieces of my thoughts after several intense key notes overloaded my brain.</p>

<p>What&#8217;s the take away? That functional languages are a lot more diverse than most OOP/procedural languages, and that there&#8217;s a lot that can be learned from them. So instead of picking your favorite and only learning that, you really should try to learn several to cover your bases.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stealing Terminology]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/07/02/stealing-terminology/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-02T22:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/07/02/stealing-terminology</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of my favorite tricks is to borrow terminology from other walks in life. This is particularly important for me, since it&#8217;s all too easy for engineers to end up living and talking in pure engineering speak. Looking to other careers for the correct words to describe something allows one to express ideas that might not be easily communicated otherwise.</p>

<p>If you look carefully, you can see examples of this in engineering blog posts. People talk about fighting entropy, or the metaphysics of data. These are terms that did not originally have any engineering context whatsoever, being brought in to express ideas and concepts about another subject.</p>

<p>My most recent borrowed term is <em>Force Multiplier</em>. A force multiplier is anything that allows an group or individual to be more effective without an increase in effort. It&#8217;s normally a military term referencing how better weather forecasts, equipment, or intelligence can allow a unit to accomplish much more without increasing effort/losses. I like to use it in reference to things like unit tests and automation, that make me more effective as an engineer without costing me more time. If I don&#8217;t have to babysit a build waiting to type in the next step, then I can get back to work while a CI server works for me. I&#8217;m instantly more effective without actually spending more time at work. With a comprehensive suite of unit tests I can spend less time worrying and validating that my refactoring has damaged the quality of the system, thus I can get more work done in the same period of time.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m sure there are far more examples of this than I&#8217;ve listed, but they&#8217;re always fun to find and analyze.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fast Cheap Good]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/06/05/fast-cheap-good/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-05T20:24:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/06/05/fast-cheap-good</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the distant past (1950&#8217;s or so), project managers and engineers came up with what is known as the project management triangle: fast, cheap, or good; pick two.</p>

<p>While software engineering can be very different from mechanical, it does at least share the same project management setup. Quality software designed cheaply will be late, cheap software released early will be poor in quality, and quality software released on time will be expensive. These differences come from the quality and number (thus cost) of the managers and engineers, the choice of methodologies, scope of features, and internal organizational setups.</p>

<p>What is different is the fact that software engineers aren&#8217;t limited by physics the way that our mechanical brethren are. With few exceptions for high performance computing, the limitation of most software projects is the imagination and effort of its engineers, not hard limits in manufacturing technologies or physics. Combine this with a fad-heavy market for programming methods (scrum! extreme! agile! pair!), and it can be very tempting to assume that we can find the perfect balance with the correct management processes and the right methodology.</p>

<p>This is false, of course. Management and methodology is about dealing with the communication overhead when enough people are working on an project. The pipe dream of management and methodology is for a group of N producers to produce N times more than one person alone. This is of course rubbish, as the <em>Mythical Man Month</em> demonstrated handily, it&#8217;s simply impossible to manage or process your way to good, cheap, and fast.</p>

<p>So what&#8217;s the point of it all then? Why don&#8217;t we just go back to waterfall? Because the point of agile, scrum, pair programming and friends is <strong>not</strong> to get us all the way to good, cheap, and fast. The point is to go from choosing one of three, to choosing two of three. A poorly managed, low discipline team can only choose one of good, cheap, and fast; and this is of course worthless. Cheap software that&#8217;s late will probably still run out of VC and be beaten by the competition. Bad and cheap software will struggle to take over the market, and software that&#8217;s both bad and late probably shouldn&#8217;t be written. However a well managed, well disciplined team can survey the market, measure the competition, and <em>knowingly</em> choose what compromises they wish to make in speed, quality, and cost. Poorly managed teams blunder into one of the choices, usually cheap and bad, and end up having very little control over their own fate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stop Surprising Me Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/06/04/stop-surprising-me-ubuntu/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-04T23:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/06/04/stop-surprising-me-ubuntu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are almost as many design principles as there are articles about them. But my two favorites are the Principle of Least Surprise, and You Ain&#8217;t Gonna Need It.</p>

<p>The Principle of Least Surprise, is one of the design principles of the language Ruby, specifically in the context of &#8220;the principle of least surprise after you learn Ruby very well.&#8221; And all good systems have the property that they do not surprise experienced users, but great systems do not even surprise inexperienced users. This is what Apple has been doing for years, trying to make their products mimic familiar scenarios and objects from the real world, so that users can simply pick up the product and use it.</p>

<p>You Ain&#8217;t Gonna Need It is actually a programming principle, stating that you should never add features under the assumption that someone might need it someday. Chances are that users either won&#8217;t need it, won&#8217;t want it, or will end up preferring something significantly different than what you provided. But I think this principle can be simplified down to &#8220;provide the minimum set of options and features to allow users to complete the task&#8221;. Simpler products are easier to learn, easier to master, and easier to create and test. The only extra work is in designing it properly.</p>

<p>With this in mind, let&#8217;s turn towards Ubuntu. I&#8217;m hardly a Linux novice, having used Gentoo, Fedora, Ubuntu, Debian, Mint, openSuse, and others before eventually converting to Mac OSX. I had to upgrade my spare Ubuntu box this week from 12.04 all the way to 13.04, and found a few gripes.</p>

<p>First of all, there&#8217;s the Amazon search feature they added sometime in the 11.X releases. It slows the search box down, which is the main way that applications are opened, and clutters up the results. Besides being a transparent money grab, I have a hard time imagining someone trying to open up their music client and suddenly deciding that they need to buy some cheese crackers <em>right now</em>. It all seems like quite a bit of distraction in order to enable a few users that want to order from Amazon without having to fire up Chrome first.</p>

<p>But the part that really angered me was when I tried to turn this &#8220;feature&#8221; off. I couldn&#8217;t find any settings within the dock itself (right clicking does nothing, it seems), and I couldn&#8217;t find any reference to it in the system settings panel either. A quick trip to Google, which I feel shouldn&#8217;t have been necessary, told me that I could turn this search off in the Privacy settings, for some reason. As annoying as this was, all would be well if the upgrade to 12.10 didn&#8217;t <strong>turn it back on again</strong>. Why would you do that to me, Ubuntu? I clearly stated that I had no interest in this mis-feature by hunting it down and disabling it, what purpose does re-enabling it have other than grab a bit more money from Amazon and anger me?</p>

<p>It&#8217;s these little mis-steps and more that make or break the user experience of a product. I&#8217;m fairly tech savvy, and am comfortable digging through StackExchange and various forums to find some solutions to my problems, but that&#8217;s not the way that the average customer works. For those who aren&#8217;t comfortable looking up answers or editing configuration files, these little details will quickly scare them away to an operating system that&#8217;s less surprising and simpler. And these are the users that Canonical must attract if they&#8217;re hoping to turn Ubuntu into a mainstream Operating System.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
