<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pairing | Ashton Kemerling]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/categories/pairing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-12-19T17:35:39-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ashton Kemerling]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ashtonkemerling@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Time, Attention, and Pairing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/10/26/time-attention-and-pairing/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-26T21:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/10/26/time-attention-and-pairing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.merlinmann.com">Merlin Mann</a> gives a great talk about Time
and Attention. The gist of his talk is that in order to create great
work, you need to balance time vs. attention. Without using your time,
you'll never create. But you must use your attention to determine if
you're creating something great. Great producers balance between these
two to both produce, and produce good work.</p>

<p>Part of my new job at <a href="http://www.pivotaltracker.com">Pivotal Tracker</a>
involves pair programming. While a lot of my programming friends express
doubt about pairing, I'm very impressed with both how productive I am
pairing, and how quickly I'm learning the code base while pairing.</p>

<p>The way that a good pair switches between who is "driving" is very
similar to Merlin's talk. The person who is typing is responsible for
producing, while the person who isn't is responsible for ensuring that
the pair is headed in the right direction. Pairs have a much easier time
finding this balance and staying on track than individual workers do.</p>

<p>It's hard to alternate between time and attention effectively when
working alone. There's no overt signal to when one is using time or
attention, making it easy to mistake "research" (reading Wikipedia) as
using your attention. As a pair this balance is much easier to achieve,
because each member is tasked with one role, and it's obvious when that
role is not being fulfilled. The non-driving member can't goof off on
Reddit or Wikipedia for the sake of "research" because it will prevent
the driving member from working. And the driving member can't slow down
too much without the other member taking over typing from them. This
helps ensure that the pair produces better code faster.</p>

<p>I'm not sure if the creators of pair programming are familiar with
Merlin's model of work, but accidentally or not they've made it much
easier for programmers to follow his advice. I'd recommend any
company to give pairing a try and see what it does for the quality and
quantity of work that their teams produce.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
