<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: philosophy | Ashton Kemerling]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/categories/philosophy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-01T14:59:42-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ashton Kemerling]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ashtonkemerling@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Swordsman and the Software Engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/06/09/the-swordsman-and-the-software-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-09T22:31:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2014/06/09/the-swordsman-and-the-software-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the largest mistakes you can make as a knowledge worker is to focus 100% of your time on your craft. It's easy to believe that specializing and focusing will make you better than your peers, but I do not think that is the case. Not only will specializing cause you to plateau earlier than your peers, it will cause you to be less happy and healthy than your diversified peers.</p>

<p>A bit of background at this point would probably be helpful. I'm a software engineer and I've coded both professionally and on a hobbyist basis for nearly a decade. After a particularly stressful few months at a previous job, my fiancé forced me to join a local gym to de-stress. The gym focused on various European martial arts and I ended up in a class for the Italian longsword circa 1409.</p>

<p>A few years ago I would have suspected that choosing to surrender 2-8 hours a week to swinging steel around instead of programming on hobbyist projects would slow down my growth. Now I believe that I owe a lot of my growth, professionally and as a human being to this practice. A lot of what I'm going to cover here will probably be old news to anyone who was heavily involved in sports, nor is it particularly unique to fencing. That being said I'm fairly confident that a lot of knowledge workers have lost the involvement with physical activities they might have had, or never were all that "athletic" even in school.</p>

<p>The biggest modern challenge is that humans are not wired for the type of work that we now do. We are a fairly clever species by nature, which is why we have been making art for hundreds of thousands of years. But we are still more or less genetically and mentally hunter gatherers from 100,000+ years ago who largely worked for their survival. Our bodies, genes, and minds are wired to expect a specific ratio of play and physical activity to signal that all is well. Unfortunately we work a lot longer than our ancestors did, and under very different conditions.</p>

<p>This high level of nothing but work, physical or mental, indicates to our bodies that times are tough and that it should release stress hormones to help us survive the coming hard times; these stress hormones tend to have serious detrimental effects on mental performance and long term health. The phrase "all work and no play" may be over-used, but it does have some truth. All work and no play leaves Jack pumped full of cortisol, short on sleep, and low on testosterone.</p>

<p>Secondly, most knowledge workers spend their entire time thinking only with their frontal cortex, or the analytical portion of the brain. This is very helpful if your job involves concentrating on difficult problems all day, but it is incredibly easy to let that portion of your brain become the only driving factor on your day to day life. The brain, like your muscles, should have ample opportunity to exercise all of its faculties and have recovery time between each heavy usage. Expecting it to be able to focus deeply on your work day in and day out without giving it time to relax is simply asking for lowered performance and burnout, and only working on one aspect of your mental performance is akin to only doing curls at the gym; the result is an odd shape with very little practical strength.</p>

<p>Thankfully exercise and hobbies help other parts of the brain. This is one of the things I love about fencing: it isn't very analytical once you actually start using it. There are a ton of cuts and guards to be memorized, but you never have time to think about it when you are actually fencing. All of the drills are designed so that your mind and body learn to move with instinctual grace from one guard to another. There is very little conscious thought that happens mid-move in a match; there simply is not enough time to stop and think. Instead you learn to have an internalized notion of time and measure, and an ability to make new decisions as the fight progresses quickly and correctly.</p>

<p>And while none of this directly relates to software engineering, it has a positive effect on my daily work. The ability to move with a fight and think with my toes and fingertips have given me a greater appreciation to the importance of gut instinct in more situations. And the constant practice of excluding my analytical mind in a fast moving match have improved my ability to enter a flow state more easily. Combine these things with the general good effects of mental down time and exercise, and I think it's hard to argue that my time would have been better spent working on hobbyist projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advanced Fear]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/10/30/advanced-existential-dread/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T19:50:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/10/30/advanced-existential-dread</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most scary moments in most young adults' life is the
realization of mortality. Teenagers and younger children often
understand on an intellectual level that people die, but emotionally
that's something that happens to other people. There's very few things
quite like the moment when an adult realizes that they must die, there's
nothing they can do to stop it, and there's not a lot they can do to
delay it.</p>

<p>Most people stop there. But if you move beyond the "go to work, make
money, enjoy weekend" stage of your life, you'll get to experience what
I call "Opportunity Cost Fear".</p>

<p>Every action you take prevents you from taking another. Spending $10 on
a lunch means you can't spend that $10 on anything else. This is called
opportunity cost. It applies to every limited resource in the
world. Your time, attention, money, emotions, energy, and physical
strength are all subject to opportunity cost, even though many people
and organizations do not think about it.</p>

<p>Those who wish to accomplish many things can suffer a crippling fear
because of it. Spending time on this blog post means I'm spending time
not reading blogs, writing software, or talking with Leah. It also means
I'm not spending my time going to the gym to be healthy, or trying to
make friends in a new city. And the fact that I can't have everything I
want, just like the fact that I can't live forever, can be deeply
terrifying if you care about doing multiple things.</p>

<p>Just like the fear of death, the best way out of opportunity cost fear
is to press forward. The big risk with both is that the fear will
cripple you to the point where the worst might as well have
happened. Are you really living if you spend every moment terrified of
your own end? What's the point worrying about opportunity cost if the
fear prevents you from executing on any of your plans? In both these
cases, the fear alone can be just as bad as the actual outcome.</p>

<p>Now, I'm not saying that the rational choice is disregard for the
objects of your fear. If you're afraid of death, riding a motorcycle
without a helmet on will neither eliminate your fear or increase your
lifespan. You should be aware of why you feared a thing, and take the
most rational steps to reduce it. Nothing you will do can ever eliminate
opportunity cost, but you can make sure that you're spending your time
as best you can. You'll never do it perfectly, but it's better than
nothing at all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Right vs. Useful]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/01/03/right-vs-useful/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T21:21:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2013/01/03/right-vs-useful</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spend a fairly decent amount of my time thinking about how my mindset and world view affects my decisions and actions. In the past few months I’ve found that how I evaluate these mindsets has begun to change; I used to be mostly concerned with whether or not a mindset was correct, but now I’ve started to think about whether or not it’s useful.</p>

<p>Determining whether or not a mindset is correct is rather tricky philosophical ground, as it requires some sort of platonic “reality” to compare it against. But for the sake of argument, let us say that a “correct” mindset matches the most unbiased observations of the world we can make, or logically follows from a set of axioms that are relatively well accepted. Good examples of correct mindsets are “Not lying on my taxes reduces the chance of getting in trouble”, and “driving according to traffic laws means I won’t get a ticket”.</p>

<p>Useful mindsets are even easier. A useful mindset is one that produces more beneficial outcomes for the user, where beneficial is also defined by the user. The best examples of useful mindsets are also correct, those who don’t speed don’t get speeding tickets, etc.</p>

<p>Where things get interesting is where useful and right don’t necessarily agree, or when it’s not currently possible to know what is correct. My particular favorite is the question of free will: It’s not currently known whether or not humans make actual decisions, or if we are merely a product of a deterministic universe.</p>

<p>Whether or not we have free will is probably beyond our current philosophical and scientific knowledge, and it’s certainly beyond mine. But we can analyze what our belief in free will does to our ability. The inputs to this scenario can be put on a 2×2 grid, 2 options for our belief (free will or not), 2 for reality (free will or deterministic), producing 4 options. If we choose to believe and free will, and free will exists we gain our own future. If we choose to believe in free will, and it doesn’t exist, we were predestined to believe as such, ditto if we don’t believe and free will doesn’t exist. But the really painful point is when we choose to not believe in free will and it exists, we end up surrendering our initiative and free well, blaming everything on fate. The obvious choice is to believe in free will, and hope for the best.</p>

<p>The more astute among you will recognize this as Pascal’s wager (which is also a form of the more general Prisoners Dilemna). Personally Pascal’s wager has never swayed my belief, as I’ve found reasons to disagree with its setup (the wager only works if you assume free will, and a vengeful Abrahamic God. If you disagree with this portrayal of a higher being, Pascal’s wager doesn’t work out the same).</p>

<p>So next time you find yourself thinking about your worldview, try using usefulness as another yardstick to compare your beliefs against.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
