<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Health | Ashton Kemerling]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/categories/health/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-08-11T11:40:20-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ashton Kemerling]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ashtonkemerling@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Revive By Totem Nutrition]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2018/06/03/revive-by-totem-nutrition/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-03T17:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2018/06/03/revive-by-totem-nutrition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Disclaimer: I am still not a doctor. Discuss with an actual doctor before beginning any diet or supplementation regime.</p>

<p>I knew I was in trouble when clapping hurt. It was a cold morning in Chicago and I was driving myself to the gym, and the shivers caused me to clap my hands together rather than rub them, resulting in a searing hot line of pain to shoot up my right forearm. For the previous few weeks something had been not right, but now it was a capital P problem.</p>

<p>A few years prior, I had joined Forteza at the prodding of my wife. Back then I was working at a startup, and things had gotten pretty stressful at work. Like, "got hospitalized due to stress triggered psychosomatic problems" stressful. Leah knew about Forteza nearby, and figured that a bit of working out and fighting would be a good outlet for my stress.</p>

<p>It turns out she was right, go figure. Forteza is a historical fencing and martial arts gym nestled into the North side of Chicago. There I learned longsword fencing, yes longsword, wrestling, and medieval dagger fighting. The work was complicated, intense, dangerous, and deeply satisfying. More importantly than the specifics of my martial career, I discovered a love for fitness and sport.</p>

<p>I had never been a good athlete. Aside from peewee soccer, my entire sports story consisted of two disappointing years of wrestling, one of which terminated early due to my low ability. For most of highschool I actually spent more time in marching band than any other physical activity, although in my defense the band was significantly more successful than our football team. At Forteza my love for fencing eventually transformed into a pursuit of fitness in general, at first to improve my fighting stamina, and later for the sake of fitness itself. I started showing up at 6AM several times a week, rain or shine, to throw around kettlebells and get stronger along with a few other crazy diehards in the cold Chicago mornings.</p>

<p>But in my car that cold November, everything was in jeopardy. my wrist was hurting badly, and nothing was helping. I couldn't hold a kettlebell with my right hand, nor could I perform the variety of snapping and rotating motions that longsword fencing requires. Something had to be done.</p>

<p>It turns out that there was something wrong with my ECU tendon, which runs from the base of my pinky along the outside of the wrist to the elbow. This tendon travels in a groove on the bone, and is held in place by a soft and flexible cover. Either due to genetics, which was my doctor's explanation, or over training, I had managed to pop the tendon out of place, doing all kinds of damage to my wrist in the process. The solution was to either undergo some serious surgery to modify my bone structure and reset the tendon, a risky and expensive proposition, or sit still on it for months on end and hope that it gets better.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this is just one of those injuries that will probably never go away. It kept me out of Forteza for the remainder of my time in Chicago, and even here in sunny LA it continues to be an occasional problem while training. Anything that involves compressing the wrist or rotating it under pressure is an injury risk for me, making some types of pushups and ring work tricky propositions that might end up in pain and reduced training.</p>

<p>The only thing I had ever found that helped my wrist was cryotherapy, which involves standing still in a -200F chamber for a few minutes. While this sounds miserable, and it is, it would almost instantly return range of pain free motion back to my wrist. It was also hard to get to, a temporary fix, and prohibitively expensive to do on a daily basis.</p>

<p>Thankfully, I've finally found a supplement that helps me out, and it's called <a href="https://www.totemnutrition.com/shop-totem/revive">Revive</a> from <a href="https://www.totemnutrition.com">Totem Nutrition</a>.</p>

<p>Revive is basically a concentrated form of one of Lucid's ingredients: Velvet Antler Extract, or VAE for short. It's a tincture, which means its a few ingredients mixed with alcohol, that you take orally. Add a few drops, or a whole dropper, under your tongue and hold it as long as you can since the alcohol burns a bit. For me I've discovered that Revive is every bit as effective as Cryotherapy over the long term, even if the effect isn't as instant as a -200F chamber can be.</p>

<p>Okay, so what's Antler Velvet? Antler Velvet is the fuzzy layer that can be seen on top of deer, elk, or moose antlers; in this case we're going to be working with Elk antler. In case you didn't know, deer and similar animals grow a fresh set of antlers <em>every year</em>, which is insane when you think about it. While the antler is growing, up to an inch a day by the way, it's covered in a fuzzy layer that contains all the support systems necessary to build an organ so quickly. Once the antler is done growing it sheds the velvet, leaving behind the hard and pointy antlers that we all know and .... love? Eventually these antlers fall off too, which is why you can occasionally find them laying around the woods in the right places.</p>

<p>Historically antler velvet was collected by hunters while hunting, which seems kind of obvious. If you're a hunter and you can get some antler velvet along with your meat, this is obviously a good deal. But for those of us who want pound after pound of the stuff, that is a short term strategy. So Totem's Elk Antler is harvested from semi-domesticated Elk. During the growing season they have their antlers trimmed, which is a bit like you or I cutting our toenails. All the work is done under the supervision of a veterinarian, just to make sure that the animals aren't hurt. Obviously this means it isn't a vegan product, sorry, but Totem promises that the Elk that lay the golden velvet are not being harmed.</p>

<p>So, what's <em>in</em> the stuff? Lot's of things, basically anything necessary to actually grow new parts of your body. For the Elk this is obviously the antlers, but for you it could be anything. One of the biggest ingredients is IGF-1, insulin like growth factor 1. IGF-1 is a protein that humans can synthesize ourselves, but we produce a lot less of it as we age. This is a problem, since IGF-1 is closely related to both mental and physical health, and is one of the reasons why exercising is so good for your brain. There's also a lot of glycosaminoglycans, which aside from being really hard to pronounce are basically building blocks for skin and joints.</p>

<p>Beyond that there's a huge list of Amino Acids that are helpful to you, including quite a few that are scientifically shown to improve your mood, including being precursors to making the happiness nerotransmitters - dopamine and seratonin. Obviously anything that helps you synthesize what's known as the "happiness nerotransmitters" is something you're going to want to have in your life.</p>

<p>Note: The ingredients in Revive are so potent that they've spent some time on and off the World Anti-Doping Agency's banned substance list. I personally think this is insane, since it's basically food and humans have been eating this stuff for millenia, but I'm also not a professional athlete who's being tested on a regular basis. If you are a professional athlete who will be tested, be sure to do your own research.</p>

<p>Totem Nutrition offers a <a href="https://www.totemnutrition.com/money-back-guarantee">no stress money back guarantee</a> if you aren't happy with their products for any reason. Best of all readers of my blog can get 10% off their first order by using the coupon code "ASHTON2018" on their first order.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lucid: A Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2018/03/10/lucid-a-review/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-10T18:45:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.ashtonkemerling.com/blog/2018/03/10/lucid-a-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Disclaimer: I am not a doctor, and this is not medical advice.</p>

<p>Sleep. We all need it, and very few of us are getting enough of it. Hectic lives, work, children, poor diets, bright screens, and insufficient exercise often result in very poor sleep for those few hours that we are actually in bed. The result is a whole nation of people driving and working while sleep deprived, resulting in car crashes, low productivity, and general negative health outcomes.</p>

<p>Side note: Did you know that people who are sleep deprived are more likely to crave carbs and overeat? Just saying.</p>

<p>None of these things are changing soon; jobs aren't becoming less hectic and screens certainly aren't becoming more rare. We all know that we need to improve our diets and exercise more, but very few of us are actually doing it. So what's to be done for the poor sleep deprived worker?</p>

<p>While most Americans would reach for drugs to fall asleep, I think supplementation is a far better answer. For the past two months I've been using <a href="https://www.totemnutrition.com/lucid-for-sleep-optimization">Lucid</a>, a supplement from Totem Nutrition, and it has radically altered my sleeping habits.</p>

<p>First off, what's the difference between a drug and a supplement? Legal definitions non-withstanding, I use the following definition: a supplement is composed of naturally occurring or extracted compounds, while a drug is a new creation that's completely new to the human body. I'm not one of those people who think that all-natural is the same as safe, since nature manages to produce some pretty poisonous stuff on its own. What I do believe is that well vetted supplements tend to be far more gentle and free from side effects than legal prescription drugs. That's been my experience at least.</p>

<p>Okay, back to Lucid. So what in the heck is it? Well it's a sleep aid, a supplement that's designed to help you fall asleep faster and sleep better. It comes in a liquid form in a dropper bottle, and you're supposed to hold it under your tongue for about a minute before you go to bed. I <em>really</em> like supplements that come in liquid form, because they're far easier to adjust the dosing on. For me, half a droppers worth of Lucid does the trick.</p>

<p>You might be tempted to compare it to drugs like Ambien, but how they work is basically completely different. Ambien is a sedative, it literally knocks you out. This might beat laying awake staring at your ceiling, but it has not been shown to improve sleep <em>quality</em>. Also, it increases your risk of doing something silly like hopping into your car naked and crashing it into your neighbor's house.</p>

<p>Rather than forcing your body to sleep, Lucid is designed to help your body through the entire sleep process. It contains the basic ingredients your body can consume in order to sleep deeply and recover from your day.</p>

<p>First of all, this supplement actually contains a few different supplements I've used on and off over the years. Melatonin (you've heard of this right?), Velvet Antler Extract, and Colostrum. I'll go over what these are and why I've used them before in a bit. Your body knows how to use these to make you sleep, among other things, but it won't overuse them. Example: Lucid contains the pre-cursor compounds for testosterone. If you're running short on this vital hormone, and yes ladies need it too, then your body can use these compounds to make more. But if you're not running low on testosterone your body <em>won't</em> overdo it, so no it won't turn you into Dolph Lundgren or anything, sorry.</p>

<p>Subjectively, I've noticed that Lucid has helped me sleep better and wake up better. I spend a lot less time in the morning trying to wake up enough to get dressed and make coffee since I've started taking Lucid. I've also noticed a marked reduction in tossing and turning, as well as the minor aches and pains that I pick up from the gym. I typically haven't struggled to fall asleep, so I can't comment on how Lucid helps me there.</p>

<p>Objectively, I've been tracking my sleep via the lovely AutoSleep app for my Apple Watch. I've noticed two different things since taking it.</p>

<p>First of all, taking Lucid has comfortably added 30 minutes to an hour of "Deep Sleep" to my nightly statistics, take a look at a <a href="/images/control.jpeg">control</a> night and a night <a href="/images/lucid.jpeg">with lucid</a>. I've also noticed fewer incidents of waking up in the middle of the night, and my sleep data shows that I'm more consistently asleep. Well, except for when the cats start crying and biting me for breakfast early. Nothing short of a serious sedative could keep me asleep through that.</p>

<p>More shockingly is what it does combined with alcohol. Alcohol is not good for your sleep, even if it does knock you out quickly. On nights where I drank and forgot my Lucid (hey, nobody is perfect) I averaged a miserable <a href="/images/alcohol.jpeg">15-30 minutes of deep sleep</a>. On nights where I drank and remembered my Lucid I got anywhere from an <a href="/images/lucidandalcohol.jpeg">hour and a half</a> to two hours of deep sleep, which is pretty close to a regular night of sleep. Look, I'm not saying that Lucid is a hangover cure, but I am definitely saying that it helped.</p>

<p>Cool, so what's in it?</p>

<ul>
<li>Melatonin - To help you get sleep.</li>
<li>Velvet Bean - Prevents a sleep hangover.</li>
<li>Vitamin B6 - Energy &amp; Mood enhancer.</li>
<li>Colostrum - Growth factors &amp; immune booster</li>
<li>Velvet Antler Extract (VAE) - Pure magic.</li>
<li>Water - Duh</li>
<li>Alcohol - To protect some of the more fragile ingredients.</li>
</ul>


<p>Velvet Antler is the one I'm most interested in. I have very fragile tendons in my wrists because of a genetic mutation I have, and statistically 1/3rd of you reading this share that mutation with me. These tendons always get sore from working out, and can strain extremely easily. I've had to miss close to a year's worth of gym time because of injuries to this part of my body. The only thing that got me back to training was cryotherapy, I'll talk about that another time, and Velvet Antler Extract.</p>

<p>So why don't I just take it alone? Well, I could, but taking VAE as part of my sleep routine is awesome. First of all, it's one less supplement to take daily, and that's great. Secondly I have to take Lucid at night, no point in making myself drowsy at lunch, which means that I get a dose of VAE right before my body does its best repair work: at night. And did I mention that I like getting a good's night sleep? What's not to love?</p>

<p>Anyways, I highly recommend that you give Lucid a try. A bottle lasts me about a month or so, and for me it's a good deal to ensure a great night's sleep.</p>

<p>Totem Nutrition, the makers of Lucid have been generous enough to offer my readers a 10% discount for trying out Lucid. Use the code "ASHTON2018" for 10% off your first order through the end of 2018.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
